We have now covered some basic things about
mapping in Elasticsearch, so let’s now get
started actually creating some mapping!
You can add field mappings both when creating
an index and afterwards.
Let’s start out defining the mapping when
creating a new index, since that’s typically
the first way that you will interact with
mapping.
We do that by defining the mappings within
a “mappings” key when we add a new index,
so let’s type that out.
All field mappings should be defined within
a “properties” key.
That’s the case for fields at every level
of the hierarchy, including nested objects
as you have already seen.
So let’s add the “properties” key.
Great, so now we are ready to define the field
mappings.
We do that by specifying the field names as
keys and add objects as the values.
I’ll add four fields; “rating,” “content,”
“product_id,” and “author.”
The “author” field is going to be an object,
so that one is a bit special.
For the three other fields, we simply define
their data type with a “type” key, so
let’s type that out.
In place of “float,” “text,” and “integer,”
you can of course use any of the data types
that you saw earlier.
The “author” field is a bit special because
it’s an object.
That’s why we need to add a “properties”
key again, just like we did at the root level
of the mapping.
This tells Elasticsearch that it is dealing
with an object containing mappings for its keys.
Within this “properties” key, we define
mappings exactly as we did at the root level
of the mapping.
In this case I will define three mappings;
“first_name,” “last_name,” and “email.”
If you wanted to, you could nest objects even
further than this.
As you know, “keyword” fields are used
for filtering and aggregations, and for exact
matches.
That’s why I chose the “keyword” data
type for the nested “email” field.
When choosing between the “text” and “keyword”
data types, it’s important to consider how
the field will be queried.
Will we need to perform a full-text search
on the e-mail address?
Probably not.
Instead, it’s much more likely that we will
be searching for all reviews left by a user
containing a specific e-mail address.
Or perhaps performing aggregations on the
e-mail address to see how many reviews a given
user has written.
An alternative to the e-mail address could
be to store the user’s ID as a number.
Alright, we are done with the mapping now,
so let’s run the query to create the index.
The index has now been created with the mapping
that we defined.
Let’s index a document into the index.
To save some time, I will just paste in the
query to do so.
Before running the query, I will just change
the e-mail address to an object, just to show
that Elasticsearch will then refuse to index
the document.
Indeed Elasticsearch refuses the document
because one of the supplied values is invalid
compared to the field’s mapping.
The reason I supplied an object and not an
integer, for instance, is that the integer
would just be coerced into a string, and Elasticsearch
would index the document as normal.
That’s the default behavior since we didn’t
disable coercion.
I’ll just revert the change and run the
query again.
The document has now been indexed correctly
and is therefore searchable.
That’s really the basics of explicitly adding
mappings, at least when creating a new index.
Before wrapping up this lecture, I just want
to mention that there is no naming convention
for field names.
As long as you are consistent, you can name
your fields however you want.
That being said, though, camelCase and snake_case
seem to be the most widely used for JSON,
so I would recommend using one of those.