Now that we have created a mapping for the
“reviews” index, I want to quickly show
you how to retrieve mappings.
Since we specified the mapping ourselves in
the previous lecture, there won’t be any
surprises here.
However, when using dynamic mapping, it may
sometimes be useful to check how Elasticsearch
has mapped fields based on the documents that
have been indexed.
To retrieve the mapping for an index, we can
send a GET request to the Mapping API as follows.
The results essentially show the same thing
that we typed out in the previous lecture.
In addition to retrieving mappings for the
entire index, it is also possible to retrieve
the mapping for a specific field.
To do that, we simply use the “field”
command, followed by the name of the field.
Let me just type that out so you can see what
it looks like.
For objects, you can specify the path of a
key using a dot notation, such as “author.email.”
That was pretty easy, right?
Now that you know how to retrieve an index’
mapping, let’s continue.