You know how to define mappings, but I only
showed you how to define them for a new index.
What if we already have an index and we want
to add a new field?
That’s what we’ll cover in this lecture.
We added a “reviews” index and defined
the mappings for it, but come to think about
it, we probably want to save the timestamp
of when the review was written as well.
Elasticsearch does not store the timestamp
of when the document was indexed, so we need
to do that ourselves.
Let’s add the mapping for a “created_at”
field.
We will still use the PUT HTTP verb, but this
time we will invoke the Mapping API.
Since we are using the Mapping API, we should
not specify the “mappings” key as we did
when creating the index.
Instead, we specify the “properties” key
at the top level of the request body.
The rest of the syntax is the same, so let’s
type everything out.
We’ll talk more about the “date” data
type in the next lecture, so let’s just
add the mapping for now.
The mapping has been added successfully.
Let’s retrieve the mapping for the index
just to be sure.
And indeed we see the field mapping within
the results.
That’s how easy it is to add mappings to
an existing index.
Let’s take a closer look at the “date”
data type now.