I still have the search results from the previous lecture
opened up, because I want to point something out.
Perhaps you already noticed how the first
document doesn’t contain the “created_at” field.
That’s because we indexed it before realizing
that we need the timestamps of when reviews
were written.
Remember how I said that fields may have zero
or more values by default?
This means that all fields are actually optional
and you are free to leave them out completely
when indexing documents.
That’s different from relational databases
where you need to explicitly allow NULL values.
But isn’t this inconvenient, you might wonder?
Well, I suppose that’s a matter of preference.
It does give you more flexibility out of the
box, but it also means that some integrity
checks need to be done at the application
level.
Elasticsearch will validate field values against
any mapping that might exist, but it won’t
reject documents that leave fields out.
To be clear, you can leave out fields even
if a mapping exists for it, so adding a field
mapping does not make the field required.
This means that you should handle this at
the application level.
There are some workarounds for doing this
in Elasticsearch, but they are neither pretty
nor convenient.
When searching for documents, you just specify
field names as normal, and Elasticsearch will
only consider documents that contain a value
for the field.
In other words, you don’t need to actively handle
if some documents may have left fields out.
That’s all I wanted to mention in this lecture,
so I’ll see you in the next one!