You have seen how to add a simple mapping
to an index, specifying fields and their data types.
Apart from specifying a field’s data type,
there are also some parameters available that
configure the behavior of fields in various
ways.
In this lecture I will give you an overview
of some of the most important parameters.
Please note that this is not an exhaustive
list of parameters, so there are other ones
available as well.
Most of them are either rarely used or quite
advanced, though.
I will come back to a couple more parameters
throughout the rest of this section when the
time is right.
With that said, let’s get started!
The first parameter is the one named “format.”
This parameter is used to specify a date format
when you want to index dates that are not
formatted in the default format.
I recommend that you use the default date
format whenever possible.
In particular the ISO 8601 format is an extremely
common format that should be supported by
almost all systems.
It might not always be possible to format
dates in one of the default formats, though;
perhaps you are integrating with a legacy
system that’s just not feasible to change.
Oftentimes you will have an event processing
pipeline such as Logstash that can reformat
data, but that might not always be the case.
That’s just to say that sometimes it might
be necessary to use non-standard date formats.
We can completely customize the date format
by specifying a format that is compatible
with Java’s DateFormatter class.
Alternatively there are a number of built-in
formats available.
Two of them are actually used within the default
format that Elasticsearch uses.
There is a rather long list of other built-in
formats that we can conveniently use instead
of building our own pattern.
An example could be if we wanted to specify
a UNIX timestamp instead of the number of
milliseconds since the epoch, in which case
we could use the “epoch_seconds” format.
I have attached a link to the documentation in case
you want to check which formats are available.
Alright, so that’s the “format” parameter.
The next parameter is actually one that you
have seen before; namely the “properties”
parameter.
We use it both at the top level when defining
mappings, and for nested fields.
To be clear, nested fields can be for both
fields of the “object” and “nested”
data types, which you can see examples of
on your screen.
Remember that even though I just mentioned
an “object” data type, there is no such
data type in Elasticsearch; instead, “object”
fields are mapped implicitly by using the
“properties” parameter instead of specifying
a type.
I won’t spend any more time on this parameter,
because you have already seen it in action,
and there is really nothing more to it.
Next up is the “coerce” parameter, which
should also be familiar to you.
Although you haven’t seen the parameter
before, we have covered the concept of coercion.
The parameter lets you enable or disable type
coercion.
It’s enabled by default, but that might
not always be desirable.
Whether or not you want it to be enabled is
really a matter of preference and how strict
you want Elasticsearch to be when indexing
documents.
You can see an example of how to disable coercion
on your screen now.
If we were to supply a string value for the
“amount” field, Elasticsearch would reject
the document.
It’s also possible to configure coercion
at the index level so you don’t have to
specify the “coercion” parameter for every
field.
Since coercion is enabled by default, it only
really makes sense to disable it at the index
level.
Fields inherit this index level setting, but
you can still overwrite it if you want to.
In the example to the right, coercion is disabled
at the index level, but the “amount” field
overwrites this and enables coercion for that
field.
Typically you will have fields that don’t
specify the “coerce” parameter and thereby
use the index level setting implicitly.
I just didn’t include such fields to keep
the example short, but I’m sure you get
the point.
Next is a parameter named “doc_values.”
This one requires us to dive a bit deeper
into Apache Lucene.
I told you what an inverted index is and how
that is used to efficiently resolve which
documents contain a given term.
I also told you that this is not the only
data structure used for fields.
That’s because there is no single data structure
that efficiently serves all purposes.
For instance, while an inverted index is excellent
for searching for terms, it doesn’t perform
well for most other use cases.
There is more to queries than simply searching
for data; perhaps we want to sort the results
alphabetically, or to aggregate values.
These are two examples of when an inverted
index does not perform well, because the access
pattern is different.
Instead of looking up terms and finding the
documents that contain them, we need to look
up the document and find its terms for a field.
This is what the “doc values” data structure
is; pretty much the opposite of an inverted index.
Besides being used for sorting and aggregations,
this data structure is also used when accessing
field values from within scripts.
To be clear, the “doc values” data structure
is not a replacement for an inverted index,
but rather an addition to it, meaning that
both data structures will be maintained for
a field at the same time.
Elasticsearch will then query the appropriate
data structure depending on the query.
Why am I telling you about this data structure
now?
Because you have the option of disabling it
with the “doc_values” mapping parameter.
But why and when would you do this?
The main reason for doing this would be to
save disk space, because this data structure
would then not be built and stored on disk.
Storing data in multiple data structures effectively
duplicates data with the purpose of fast retrieval,
so disk space is traded for speed.
A side benefit of that would be increased
indexing speed, because there is naturally
a small overhead of building this data structure
when indexing documents.
So when would you want to disable doc values?
If you know that you won’t need to use a
field for sorting, aggregations, and scripting,
you can disable doc values and save the disk
space required to store this data structure.
For small indices, it might not matter much,
but if you are storing hundreds of millions
of documents, there will be a significant
difference.
It’s important to note that if you disable
doc values, you cannot change this without
reindexing all of your data.
This actually applies to many mapping parameters
as you will see soon.
This means that you really have to consider
which kinds of queries you run against your
data and try to anticipate how you will query
your data in the future.
This is also why you should consider this
an advanced parameter, and you should probably
not use it unless you have a reason for doing
so.
Typically that would be if you are storing
a large number of documents, or if you anticipate
that you will.
Before continuing, here is how doc values
can be disabled within a field’s mapping.
Next up, we have a parameter named “norms.”
We haven’t covered what norms are yet, so
I will just give you a quick introduction here.
Norms refers to the storage of various normalization
factors that are used to compute relevance scores.
We haven’t gotten into search queries yet,
but oftentimes we will want to not just apply
a filter to documents, but also rank them
based on how well they match a given query.
Think of search results on Google, for instance.
The results on page five are naturally not
as relevant as the ones on the first page.
That’s because they are sorted based on
relevance, and the same is done for some queries
in Elasticsearch.
Part of what enables Elasticsearch to calculate
relevance scores for documents, is these norms.
As with many other things, they are stored
within Apache Lucene, but that’s besides
the point.
What the “norms” mapping parameter enables
us to do, is to disable these norms.
Why?
Because they take up quite a lot of disk space,
just like doc values do.
Not storing norms saves disk space, but also
removes the ability to use a field for relevance scoring.
That’s why you should only disable norms
for fields that you won’t use for relevance scoring.
For example, you might have a “tags” field
for products as you saw earlier in the course.
Such a field would almost always be used for
either filtering or aggregations.
We can use the field for these use cases just
fine, because they don’t involve relevance scoring.
In such a scenario, it makes perfect sense
to not store the norms at all, because they
are just a waste of disk space.
A “name” field for a product, however,
would almost always be used for relevance
scoring because we would probably be performing
full-text searches on the field.
So if you know that you will only use a field
for filtering and aggregations, then you can
save disk space by disabling norms.
I hope that makes sense.
It’s also possible to ignore a field in
terms of indexing, by setting the “index”
parameter to “false.”
By doing so, the field values are not indexed
at all, and the field therefore cannot be
used within search queries.
It’s important to note that the field value
will still be stored within the “_source”
object; it just won’t be part of the data
structures used for searching.
This parameter is useful if you have a field
that you don’t need to search, but you still
want to store the field as part of the “_source”
object.
Not indexing a field naturally saves disk
space and slightly increases the rate at which
documents can be indexed.
This parameter is often used for time series
data where you have numeric fields that you
won’t use for filtering, but rather for
aggregations.
Even if you disable indexing for a field,
you can still use it for aggregations.
That’s because those work a bit differently,
but I don’t want to get into that right now.
Just two more parameters, so hang in there!
In a previous lecture, we talked about how
missing field values are handled, i.e. if
a field is left out when indexing a document.
But what if we include the field and supply
NULL as the value?
NULL values are ignored in Elasticsearch,
meaning that they cannot be indexed or searched.
The same applies to an empty array, or an
array of NULL values.
If you want to be able to search for NULL
values, then you can use the “null_value”
parameter to replace NULL values with a value
of your choice.
Whenever Elasticsearch encounters a NULL value
for the field, it will index the value specified
by the parameter instead, thereby making this
value searchable.
There are a couple of things to note about
this parameter.
First, it only works for explicit NULL values,
meaning that providing an empty array does
not cause Elasticsearch to perform the replacement.
Secondly, the value that you define must be
of the same data type as the field’s data
type.
If the field is an integer, then you must
supply an integer value to the parameter.
Lastly, the parameter influences how data
is indexed, meaning the data structures that
are used for searches.
The “_source” object is therefore not
affected, and will contain the value that
was supplied when indexing the document, i.e.
NULL.
Time for the last parameter - I promise!
Suppose that we have the name of a person
stored as two fields; “first_name” and
“last_name.”
While we can query one or both of these fields
just fine, we might also want to index the
full name into a third field, perhaps named
“full_name.”
That’s possible with the “copy_to” parameter.
The value for the parameter should be the
name of the field to which the field value
should be copied.
So by adding the parameter to both the “first_name”
and “last_name” fields, Elasticsearch
will copy both values into the “full_name”
field.
Notice how I said that values will be copied.
That’s because it’s not the tokens or
terms yielded by the analyzer that are copied;
instead, it’s the values that were supplied.
These values are then analyzed with the analyzer
of the target field.
One important thing to note is that the copied
values will not be part of the “_source” object.
In this example it means that the “full_name”
field is not part of the “_source” object,
since the values are only indexed.
The exception to that is if you specify a
value for the “full_name” field when you
index the document, but that’s not a very
common thing to do at all.
Alright, that’s the end of this overview.
As I mentioned at the beginning of the lecture,
we didn’t cover all mapping parameters here.
We will get back to a couple more important
ones throughout the remainder of this section.
The chances that you will use the rest are
pretty slim, so I will leave you to explore
those within the documentation if you want
to.