A bit earlier you saw how to add new field
mappings to an existing index.
But what about updating an existing field
mapping?
The “reviews” index currently contains
a “product_id” field of the type “long.”
That data type has served us well, but for
whatever reason our product IDs may now contain
letters, so we need to change it.
We won’t be performing full-text searches
on the field, so the “text” data type
doesn’t make sense.
Instead, we will use the field for filtering,
i.e. to find the reviews for a given product.
That narrows the data type down to “keyword,”
which is the one we will use.
So how do we actually change the field’s
mapping?
Can we just use the same query that we used
to add a new field mapping to an existing
index?
I have it typed out already, so let’s try.
As you can see, we get an error stating that
the provided data type is different from the
existing one.
The reason is that in general, we cannot update
field mappings in Elasticsearch.
We can add new field mappings as we did earlier,
but once you have added a field mapping, you
are pretty much stuck with it.
There is one exception, though; some mapping
parameters can be updated, but only a few
of them.
Consider the second query on your screen now.
It contains the current mapping for the “email”
field that is nested within the “author”
field.
I will add one of the parameters that can
be added to existing field mappings; namely
the “ignore_above” parameter.
This parameter ignores strings longer than
the specified value such that they will not
be indexed or stored.
As you can see, we were indeed able to modify
the field mapping to include this parameter.
Chances are, though, that you will not be
able to update a field mapping once you have
created it.
There are a number of reasons for that, with
one of the main ones being that documents
might already have been indexed with the existing
field mapping.
If we could just change the mapping, we would
have to reindex any existing documents.
For instance, changing a “text” field
to a “keyword” field is not possible,
because values have already been analyzed.
Our failed attempt to change the “long”
data type to “keyword” also didn’t work.
Remember how numeric values are indexed into
a BKD tree.
Switching to the “keyword” data type would
require that data structure to be converted
to an inverted index, which is essentially
the same as reindexing all of the field’s values.
If you have indexed many millions of documents,
that is going to take a while.
Even if we haven’t indexed any documents
since adding a field mapping, we are still
not allowed to update it.
On top of that, you also cannot remove a field
mapping once you have added it.
While that may sound strange, remember that
the mapping will not be used if a field value
is not supplied when indexing a document,
so we can simply ignore the field moving forward.
If we want to reclaim the storage space used
by the field, we could use the Update By Query
API and remove the field from each matching
document with a script.
There are all kinds of challenges involved
with updating existing field mappings, some
of which don’t even have to do with changing
the data type.
Changing a field mapping almost always requires
documents to be reindexed.
That’s why Elasticsearch protects us by
simply not allowing existing mappings to be
updated - except for a small number of parameters.
So if we cannot update the data type for our
“product_id” field, then what do we do?
We create a new index with the updated mapping
and reindex any existing documents into it.
Let’s see how to do that in the next lecture.