Alright, so as we talked about in the previous
lecture, changing how documents are mapped
usually requires reindexing documents.
The first step is to create a new index and
define the new mapping and optionally any
index settings.
Let’s create an updated version of the “reviews”
index where the “product_id” field is
of the “keyword” data type.
To save some typing, let’s retrieve the
current mapping and copy/paste that into
the query.
All
we need to do now is to modify the data type
for the “product_id” field.
That’s it.
Let’s run the query.
The index has now been created and we are
ready to add documents to it.
But how do we do that?
We could write a script that retrieves documents
from the old index, modifies them in one way
or another, and then indexes them into the
new index.
That takes quite a bit of work, especially
if we want to reindex a large number of documents.
Instead, Elasticsearch exposes a convenient
API specific to this purpose, namely the Reindex
API.
This API does the heavy lifting of moving
documents from one index to another so that
we don’t have to.
That’s because reindexing documents is actually
a pretty common thing to do during the lifetime
of an index.
Business requirements may change, or perhaps
we need to tweak how data is stored when scaling
from thousands to hundreds of millions of
documents.
Whatever the case, let’s begin typing out
the query that moves documents from the old
index into the new one.
The HTTP verb is “POST” and the endpoint
is simply “_reindex.”
We will need to define two parameters named
“source” and “dest,” both being objects.
Let’s add those to the request body.
The “source” parameter defines where the
documents should be retrieved from and how
to retrieve them.
For now, let’s just define the index name
within a parameter named “index.”
Next, let’s define where the documents should
be stored, which we also specify with an “index”
parameter, this time within
the “dest” parameter.
That’s the basic query for reindexing documents.
Let’s run it and see what happens.
Everything appears to have worked, and the
results state that five documents were reindexed.
Let’s retrieve the documents within the
new index to verify that everything looks index.
Indeed the five documents are returned.
At a glance, everything looks good, but if
we take a closer look, notice how the values
for the “product_id” field are numeric
and not strings.
To be clear, this has no effect on how the
values are indexed - specifically in regards
to the inverted index.
This is only a cosmetic thing within the “_source”
object.
Remember that this object contains the original
values that were supplied at index time.
Us changing the data type doesn’t cause
the “_source” object to be modified.
However, when performing search requests,
you will typically grab field values from
the “_source” object, and it would be
fair to assume that you would get a string
value back for a “keyword” field.
That’s why it might be a good idea to modify
the source document while reindexing the documents.
Alternatively you can just convert the data
type within whatever application is querying
the index, but I prefer for Elasticsearch
to return the expected data type.
The way that we can modify documents during
reindexing, is to supply a script that is
run for each document.
I will just paste in a query with the script
to save a bit of typing.
The script is defined within a “source”
parameter, which is nested within the “script”
parameter.
We haven’t talked much about scripting yet,
although you have seen some simple examples
earlier.
That’s why this example is also a very simple
one.
It checks if the “product_id” field is
defined within the source document, first
of all.
That’s because our reviews didn’t contain
a product ID from the beginning, so one of
our documents does not contain this field.
If we left out this check, we would get a
NullPointerException for that document.
Anyway, the following line simply replaces
the value of the “product_id” field within
the source document with the existing value
converted to a string.
Let’s delete the documents within the new
index and reindex the documents again.
To do that, we will use the Delete by Query
API.
I have prepared the query in advance, so let’s
just go ahead and run it.
Now
that the documents have been reindexed once
again, let’s verify that the product IDs
have been converted to strings within the
“_source” object.
And indeed they have.
Awesome!
Alright, let me show you a couple of slightly
more advanced use cases.
We’ll be leaving Kibana for this, because
I don’t want to spend a lot of time typing
out queries when I can just show them to you
on a slide.
If you want to take them for a spin, by all
means go ahead and run them within Kibana.
You can find the queries within the GitHub
repository so that you can copy and paste
them.
The first thing I will show you is that we
can specify a query within the “source”
parameter to only reindex documents that match
the query.
That’s useful if we only want to reindex
a subset of the documents that are stored
within the source index.
Since we haven’t covered search queries
yet, I have just specified the “match_all”
query.
That doesn’t really make sense because that’s
the same as not specifying a query.
Let’s make it a bit more interesting and
meaningful by specifying a query that matches
reviews with a rating of at least 4.0.
Don’t worry about the specifics of the query,
although it’s actually pretty straightforward.
Running this reindex query would only reindex
reviews with a rating of at least 4.0.
Pretty cool, right?
Next, suppose that we want to remove a field.
As you know, we cannot delete a field mapping,
so that is not an option.
As you also know, we can just leave out the
field when indexing new documents and leave
things as is.
However, if we have indexed lots of documents,
perhaps we want to reclaim the disk space
used by the field.
Remember that even though we stop supplying
a value for a field when indexing new documents,
the existing values are still maintained within
a data structure.
Depending on how many values have been indexed,
this may use a considerable amount of disk
space that we could use for other things.
That’s of course assuming that we won’t
need to query these values in the future.
The way we can do this is to use so-called
“source filtering.”
By specifying an array of field names, only
those fields are included for each document
when they are indexed into the destination
index.
In other words, any fields that you leave
out will not be reindexed.
It’s possible to do the same thing with
a script, but using the “_source” parameter
is a simpler approach.
Sometimes you might want to rename a field,
such as renaming the “content” field to
“comment.”
That can be done with a script consisting
of just one statement.
In case you were wondering, the “_source”
key translates to a Java HashMap.
Besides removing a key, the “remove” method
also returns its value, which is why the assignment
works.
Just as with scripted updates, it’s possible
to specify the operation for the document
within the script.
That’s done by assigning a value to the
“op” property on the “ctx” variable.
You can assign a value of either “noop”
or “delete.”
In the case of “noop,” the document will
not be indexed into the destination index.
This is useful if you have some advanced logic
to determine whether or not you need to reindex
documents.
In this example we only reindex reviews with
a rating of at least 4.0.
Note that it will usually be enough to define
a query that matches the documents, but for
advanced use cases that might not always be
possible.
In this particular example, we could just
as well have defined a query that expresses
this constraint, which you actually saw how
to do earlier.
That approach is actually much better in terms
of performance, so you should always prefer
specifying a query whenever possible.
Setting the operation to “delete” causes
the document to be deleted within the destination
index.
This can be useful because the document might
already exist within that index.
In this lecture we reindexed documents into
an empty index, but that might not always
be the case; there is nothing preventing us
from using the Reindex API to move documents
into a non-empty index.
The API is just typically used for new indices
when changing mappings, but it is not limited
to just that use case.
That being said, you can typically achieve
the same thing by using the Delete by Query
API instead.
There are more parameters available for the
Reindex API than the ones we covered in this
lecture.
For example, you can define how to handle
version conflicts, just as with the Update
by Query API.
That’s because the Reindex API also makes
a snapshot of the index before indexing documents
into the destination index.
By default, the operation is aborted if a
version conflict is encountered.
That’s fine when the destination index is
empty, but that might not be the case.
Just like the Update by Query and Delete by
Query APIs, the Reindex API also performs
the operations in batches by using the Scroll
API.
That’s essentially how it’s able to handle
millions of documents efficiently.
You can define parameters that are related
to throttling and limiting the number of requests
per second.
That’s useful if you need to reindex a lot
of documents on a production cluster and you
want to limit the performance impact.
Anyway, that all becomes more complicated
than what I want to cover here.
The point is that if you intend to use this
API for millions of documents at once, then
I recommend that you take a look at the documentation
attached to this lecture.