In the previous lecture, I showed an example
of how we could change the name of a field
when reindexing documents into a new index.
That’s useful if you need to reindex documents
anyway, but if you have millions of documents,
it’s probably not worth the effort to reindex
them just for the sake of renaming a field.
In this lecture I will show you an alternative
that doesn’t require documents to be reindexed.
What we can do instead, is to use aliases.
Let’s implement the example from the previous
lecture, being to change the “content”
field to “comment.”
Instead of actually renaming the field, we
can add an alias pointing to the actual field,
which we can then use in our queries instead
of the original name.
The way we do that is to add a new field mapping,
which you have seen how to do already.
We use a data type named “alias” and specify
the aliase’s target field name within a
parameter named “path.”
Let’s type that out.
two search queries prepared that simply search
the original field and the alias, respectively.
I’m sure you can imagine that the first
query works as it always has, but let’s
quickly run it to be sure.
If we specify the “comment” field instead,
we should get the same results.
Indeed the results are the same.
A field alias is useful in situations where
you want to rename a field but don’t want
to reindex data just for that purpose.
While adding an alias does not get rid of
the existing field mapping, it does let you
query a field by a different name.
A field alias is actually one of the few examples
of mappings that can be updated.
Not its name, but its target field.
If you want to change the field that an alias
points to, you can simply perform a mapping
update with a new value for the “path”
parameter.
That’s possible because an alias has no
influence on how values are indexed; it is
simply a construct used when parsing queries,
whether it’s a search or index request.
On the diagram, you can see how the “comment”
alias is translated into the field name that
it points to for both an index request and
a search query.
After translating the alias into the original
field name, a query is handled in exactly
the same way as it would have if the original
field name was specified.
That’s essentially all there is to field
aliases.
There are a few limitations in how you can
use them, but none that you are likely to
come across; for all common use cases, you
can utilize aliases as you would expect.
It is also possible to configure index aliases
at the cluster level, which is useful in a
number of use cases, particularly when dealing
with high volumes of data.
Anyway, I don’t want to get into that in
this section of the course, but I just wanted
to mention it because it is related.