The first topic that we will cover is analysis.
You might also see this topic being referred
to as text analysis.
That’s because the concept is really only
applicable to text values.
When we index a text value, it goes through
an analysis process.
This process involves a number of things that
I will get back to.
The purpose of it is to store the values in
a data structure that is efficient for searching.
When we retrieved documents in the previous
section, you saw how the values that we indexed
were returned under an “_source” key.
This object contains the exact values that
we specified when indexing a document.
However, those are not the values that Elasticsearch
uses internally when figuring out which documents
match a search query.
That’s because a long product description,
for instance, cannot be searched efficiently
without processing it first.
I will tell you the specifics of how Elasticsearch
stores data soon, but for now the point is
that text is processed before being stored.
When a text value is indexed, a so-called
analyzer is used to process the text.
In other words, the value is analyzed.
An analyzer consists of three building blocks;
character filters, a tokenizer, and token filters.
The result of analyzing text values is then
stored in a searchable data structure.
Let’s go over the parts of an analyzer one
by one, beginning with character filters.
A character filter receives the original text
and may transform it by adding, removing,
or changing characters.
An analyzer may have zero or more character
filters, and they are applied in the order
in which they are specified.
An example could be to remove HTML elements
and convert HTML entities by using a character
filter named “html_strip.”
An analyzer must contain exactly one tokenizer,
which is responsible for tokenizing the text.
By “tokenizing,” I am referring to the
process of splitting the text into tokens.
As part of that process, characters may be
removed, such as punctuation, exclamation
marks, etc.
An example of that could be to split a sentence
into words by splitting the string whenever
a whitespace is encountered.
The input string is therefore tokenized into
a number of tokens.
Although you don’t see it in this example,
the tokenizer also records the character offsets
for each token in the original string.
You will learn why this is the case later
in the course, so I chose to keep the example
as simple as possible for now.
Next, we have token filters.
These receive the tokens that the tokenizer
produced as input and they may add, remove,
or modify tokens.
As with character filters, an analyzer may
contain zero or more token filters, and they
are applied in the order in which they are
specified.
The simplest possible example of a token filter
is probably the “lowercase” filter, which
lowercases all letters.
Elasticsearch ships with a number of built-in
character filters, tokenizers, and token filters.
As you can probably imagine, it is possible to mix and match these together to form custom analyzers.
We will get back to that later in this section,
but let’s keep things simple for now.
Let’s walk through an example of what happens by default when Elasticsearch encounters a text value.
No character filter is used by default, so
the text is passed on to the tokenizer as is.
The tokenizer splits the text into tokens
according to the Unicode Segmentation algorithm.
Its implementation is a bit technical, but
essentially it breaks sentences into words
by whitespace, hyphens, and such.
In the process, it also throws away punctuation
such as commas, periods, exclamation marks, etc.
It’s a bit more complicated than this, but
it pretty much behaves the way you would expect.
The tokens are then passed on to a token filter
named “lowercase.”
This token filter does what you would expect;
it lowercases all letters for the tokens.
What you just saw is the behavior of the “standard”
analyzer.
This analyzer is used for all “text” fields
unless configured otherwise.
There are a couple of analyzers available
besides the “standard” analyzer, but that’s
the one you will typically use.
It’s also possible to build your own one
like I mentioned a moment ago.
I will give you an overview of the most important
analyzers, character filters, tokenizers,
and token filters a bit later in this section.
All you need to know for now is what analyzers
do and how the “standard” analyzer behaves.