In this lecture we will look at something
called index templates.
Perhaps you can guess what it is based on
the name.
An index template defines settings and/or mappings for indices that match one or more patterns.
A pattern is a wildcard expression that is
matched against an index name whenever a new
index is created, and so index templates only
apply to new indices.
Let me show you what an index template looks
like, and then I will get back to when they are useful.
To save some typing, I have already prepared
part of the query to add a new index template.
Specifically, I have already defined the mappings
for a couple of fields, because that part
doesn’t contain anything you haven’t seen
before.
Well, almost, but I will get back to that.
We can add a new index template by using the Index Template API together with the PUT HTTP verb.
The request path is “_template” followed
by the name of the index template.
I have named the template “access-logs”
because it’s going to define mappings for
indices storing HTTP access logs.
There is one important part missing, though;
the index patterns that define which indices
this template should be applied to.
Those should be defined within an “index_patterns”
parameter consisting of an array of strings.
As mentioned a moment ago, index patterns
are essentially index names where parts of
them may be wildcards.
You don’t have to use wildcards, so you
can perfectly fine just specify the exact
index names, but that probably defeats the
purpose of using an index template.
In this case I will specify an index pattern
with an asterisk wildcard at the end.
So what’s the point of this pattern?
Elasticsearch is often used to store time
series data, which can be a lot of different
things, just as long as the entries are sorted
chronologically.
Typically an equal amount of time will occur between each data point, but that is not a requirement.
For example, we could capture and store the
hardware usage of servers every minute, or
perhaps every second.
Or we could ping an API endpoint to store
uptime information.
This is actually what Metricbeat and Heartbeat
does, respectively.
In fact, they also utilize index patterns
to apply mappings and index settings.
So why did I include a wildcard at the end
of the index pattern?
Because time series data is often divided
into multiple indices.
How many depends on the data volume, so it could be per year, month, week, or day, for  instance.
A common approach is to create one index per
day for large data volumes.
Think millions of entries per day.
For fewer entries, you could get away with
far fewer indices.
There are numerous reasons for doing this,
but I don’t want to get into details now.
For monthly indices, the index names could
look like this.
For daily indices, a common pattern is the
following.
Those index names are all matched by our pattern.
This means that if we create a new index for
tomorrow’s access logs, the mappings that
we have defined will automatically be created.
Pretty cool, right?
Apart from specifying mappings, an index template
can also contain index settings.
Let’s specify the number of shards, first
of all.
The format is the same as you saw earlier
in the course, so let me just type that out.
Just as you have seen before, we could also
define the number of replica shards here if
we wanted to.
Instead, I am going to disable type coercion.
Disabling it at the index level means that
every field inherits the setting and uses
it unless it is overridden.
Alright, let’s run the query to add the
index template.
Now that the index template has been added,
let’s create a new index that matches the
index pattern of the template.
Specifically, an index to contain access logs
for the 1st of January, 2020.
Let’s inspect the index to ensure that both
the mapping and settings were applied as expected.
For that, we can simply specify the index
name and use
the “GET” HTTP verb.
Within the results, we indeed see both the
mapping and the settings that we specified
within the index template.
Awesome!
Alright, just a few more things to mention
before ending this lecture.
If a new index matches the pattern of an index template, those settings and mappings will be used.
However, if the request to create the new
index also specifies settings or mappings,
the two will be merged together.
In case of duplicates, the configuration from
the create index request will take precedence
and override the value specified within the
index template.
You can see that on the example diagram where
the index template specifies that indices
should have two shards and two replica shards.
When creating an index, the “number_of_shards”
setting is present with a value of three.
This is merged together with the settings
from the index template.
Since there is a duplicate entry, the setting
from the index template is overriden.
The result is therefore three shards and two
replica shards.
A new index may also match more than one index
template.
Index templates can be created with an “order”
parameter which is simply an integer value
representing the priority of the template.
This is used to control which settings take
precedence in cases where an index matches
multiple templates.
Index templates can be updated with new mappings
and settings.
To do this, simply use the same API as when creating the template and send the full new configuration.
This only affects new indices; existing indices
that matched the index template are left untouched.
An index template can be retrieved and deleted
by using the same endpoint with the “GET”
and “DELETE” HTTP verbs, respectively.
Lastly, you might have wondered why I named
the fields the way I did.
Those field names were definitely not the
shortest and simplest ones that I could have chosen.
That’s due to something called the Elastic
Common Schema, which we will take a look at
in the next lecture, so I will see you there!