I mentioned something called the Elastic Common
Schema (abbreviated ECS) in the previous lecture.
So, what is it?
ECS is a specification that defines a set
of common fields, including their names and
how they should be mapped in Elasticsearch.
ECS came to life as the number of products
within the Elastic Stack grew.
Values were ingested into Elasticsearch using
different field names depending on the source,
and so there was no cohesion between the mappings.
This was both confusing and inconvenient.
For instance, a Kibana dashboard needed to
know which particular web server was being
used because the field names were different
- at least when using Filebeat modules.
There was really no standard, and so the fields
were often named something along the lines
of “apache2.access.url” or “nginx.access.url.”
This was inconvenient because the data consumer
— such as Kibana — needed to know the
event source implementation.
However, once access logs are parsed, it makes
no difference if the web server that generated
them is named Apache or nginx.
Changing the web server would cause all kinds
of trouble all the way through the ingestion
pipeline because the field names would then
be different.
Therefore we want to keep the field names
the same so that Kibana doesn’t need to
know if events come from an Apache or nginx
web server.
Realistically, you don’t change a web server
that often, but it is a dependency nonetheless.
It’s pretty common to ingest data from a
number of sources at the same time, though.
For instance, we might want to collect data
from a number of different services such as
a Postgres database, Kafka, nginx, and perhaps
a Redis cluster.
We would probably process an event once per
minute, and we would need to store this timestamp
within a field.
Instead of having each service potentially
name this field differently, the ECS specification
states that it should be named @timestamp.
This means that no matter which kind of event
you are dealing with, this should be the name
of when the event originated.
This makes it easier when consuming data — perhaps
through Kibana — because the name of the
timestamp field is the same regardless of
the event source.
Note that the @timestamp field is used for
events; you might still have a field named
“created_at” for products, for instance.
ECS was created to overcome the challenges of having different field names for the same things.
Naturally, ECS is not just related to web
server logs.
In fact, ECS is not intended to support a
fixed set of use cases.
It defines a lot of common fields in various
groups, such as network fields, geolocation
fields, operating system fields, etc.
These groups are referred to as field sets.
If we take a look at the documentation, you
can see all of the field sets at the right-hand
side of the page if we expand the “ECS Field
Reference” menu item.
All of these field sets total hundreds of
fields covering many different kinds of fields.
In ECS terminology, documents are referred
to as events.
That’s because ECS includes fields for most
event types that are generated by a lot of
different technologies.
If you want to store data such as employees,
companies, products, orders, etc., then ECS
does not provide fields for this.
That’s because those are specific to your
use case, so there is no standard for them.
ECS is mostly useful if you are storing standard
events such as web server logs, operating
system metrics, geospatial data, etc.
In that case you should try to structure your
data using ECS, because then you can utilize
Kibana dashboards without having to reconfigure
field names, for instance.
That being said, you will often be using Filebeat
or Metricbeat for this, which structure data
according to ECS automatically.
For instance, if you ingest web server logs
with Filebeat, you won’t have to deal with
ECS at all, because it has already been handled
for you.
ECS is therefore mostly useful when building
custom implementations that don’t involve
other Elastic Stack products.
This means that you typically won’t actively
deal with ECS, but it’s good to be aware
of it and that it is being used across the
Elastic Stack.
For custom implementations, it’s not a big
deal if you don’t make use of ECS fields
to be honest; consider it a best practice
and recommendation.
For most use cases, you won’t have to actively
deal with ECS, so the purpose of this lecture
is mainly just to tell you what ECS is about.
I have attached the link to the documentation if you want to explore ECS and the fields that it provides.