So far in this section, we have worked with
explicit mappings, although I did briefly
mention the concept of dynamic mapping.
Dynamic mapping is what we will be working
with now.
It’s essentially a way to make Elasticsearch
easier to use by not requiring us to define
explicit field mappings before indexing documents.
The first time Elasticsearch encounters a
field, it will automatically create a field
mapping for it, which is then used for subsequent
indexing requests.
Suppose that we index a document into an index
that either doesn’t exist yet, or one that
doesn’t contain any mappings.
We specify three fields, none of which Elasticsearch
has seen before, so it automatically creates
a mapping for each field.
Let’s have a look at the field mappings
that would be generated.
The “created_at” field was mapped to the
“date” data type, even though we specified
a string as the value.
That’s because there is no “date” data
type in JSON, so Elasticsearch uses a process
called date detection to… well, detect dates.
I will get back to that in a moment.
The “in_stock” field was mapped to the
“long” data type because we specified
a numeric value without decimals.
In this case an integer would be sufficient
and save us some disk space, but Elasticsearch
cannot know how large numbers we intend to
store for a field, so it always chooses the
“long” data type.
When storing millions of documents, it might
be worth explicitly mapping the field as an
integer instead.
The “tags” field was interestingly mapped
as a multi-field with both the “text”
and “keyword” data types.
Notice how the keyword mapping is named “keyword,”
which follows the naming convention that I
mentioned earlier.
The reasoning behind this mapping is that
Elasticsearch doesn’t know how you intend
to query fields.
That’s why it adds two mappings, which can
be used for different use cases; the “text”
mapping should be used for full-text searches,
while the “keyword” mapping should be
used for exact matches, aggregations, and
sorting.
You should think of this as a sensible default behavior, but it might not always be the best mapping.
In this example, it’s quite unlikely that
we will be performing full-text searches on
tags; we will probably only do two things,
being to filter documents based on exact matches,
and to do aggregations.
This means that the “text” mapping would
be unused, and it would just cause indexing
overhead and a waste of disk space.
On the contrary, a “description” field
would rarely be used for aggregations or sorting,
because that just wouldn’t make any sense.
We would perform full-text searches on such a field, rendering the “keyword” mapping redundant.
This brings me to the “ignore_above” parameter
that has a value of 256.
This simply ignores strings that are more
than 256 characters long, causing the value
to not be part of the inverted index for the
“keyword” mapping.
This is done because it almost never makes
sense to use such long values for sorting
and aggregations.
In such a case, the values just use unnecessary
disk space, because the data is effectively
duplicated for each mapping.
As an optimization to always provide both
mappings, Elasticsearch ignores long values
for the “keyword” mapping.
That’s just to avoid storing long texts
twice, such as product descriptions or blog posts.
If you index values that are less than 256
characters long and you don’t make use of
the “keyword” mapping, then it’s still
a waste of disk space, but the impact is reduced.
Therefore you should consider this default mapping a sensible default that is used for convenience.
If you know that you won’t need either of
the two mappings, then you should consider
adding your own mapping as an optimization.
If you just store a few thousand documents,
it’s really not a big deal, but if you anticipate
that you will scale an index up to many million
documents, then the savings will eventually
be significant.
You just saw three examples of how Elasticsearch
maps data types into field mappings.
Let’s take a look at the rules that are
used to determine how fields are mapped dynamically.
When a string value is encountered, it is
typically mapped to a “text” field which
has a nested “keyword” mapping.
There are two exceptions to this, with the
first one being if the value passes date detection.
By default, values are checked against the
date formats that you see on your screen now,
but this can be configured.
Perhaps you noticed how the table shows that
strings can also be mapped to “float”
or “long” fields.
This is done with numeric detection, which
is essentially coercion.
If a string contains only a number, numeric
detection will map the field as either “float”
or “long,” depending on the value.
This behavior is actually disabled by default,
hence why I have listed the data types in parenthesis.
You can enable it if you want to, but that’s
not the best practice.
Instead, you can map numeric fields explicitly,
and if numbers are sent to Elasticsearch as
strings, coercion will take care of the rest.
Even better, you should ensure that numbers
are always sent to Elasticsearch as numbers
instead of strings.
Numeric detection and coercion are essentially
ways for Elasticsearch to be forgiving, but
you should try to not rely on them.
Next, integers are mapped to the “long”
data type.
As I mentioned earlier, Elasticsearch has
no way of knowing how large numbers you intend
to store, so it chooses the “long” data
type just in case.
Floating point numbers and booleans are mapped
to “float” and “boolean,” so no surprises there.
Objects are mapped to… well, objects.
As you know, objects are a bit special, since
there is no data type named “object,”
so it’s an implicit data type you could
say.
Here is an example of how an object would
be mapped using dynamic mapping.
Each key-value pair within the “cpu” object
will be mapped using the same rules as any
other field.
Lastly, let’s talk about how arrays are
mapped.
As you know, the mapping won’t be any different
than other fields because every field in Elasticsearch
may contain zero or more values, so there
is no need to define this.
The difference is how Elasticsearch infers
the data type.
It does so based on the first non-null value
in the array.
That value is used to determine the data type
based on the same rules as shown in the diagram.
Apart from the aforementioned rules, specifying
a NULL value for a field will cause Elasticsearch
to completely ignore that field and not add
a mapping for it.
Remember the “products” index that we
created earlier in the course?
We indexed a thousand documents into it without
adding any mappings first.
Since dynamic mapping is enabled by default,
the field mappings were created for us automatically
based on the field values that we supplied
to the Bulk API.
Let’s take a short moment to inspect the
mapping.
Spoiler alert, it’s going to look pretty similar to what you have already seen in this lecture.
Looking at the mapping, it hopefully looks
as you expected.
Just a small thing to note.
Both the “description” and “tags” fields are mapped as “text” and “keyword” fields.
Nothing new about that.
However, this is one example of how dynamic
mapping does not always map things in the
most efficient way.
In this case, we could do without the “keyword”
mapping for the “description” field, and
the “text” mapping for the “tags”
field.
That would cause documents to take up less
storage space and also slightly increase the
indexing throughput.
Those were the very basics of dynamic mapping.
Let’s continue.