Now that you know how dynamic mapping maps
values to field mappings by default, let’s
take a look at how it can be configured.
The most important thing to know is how to
disable dynamic mapping, so that’s where
we will start.
I have the same queries prepared as in the
previous lecture.
To configure whether dynamic mapping should
be enabled or disabled, we can specify a boolean
value for the “dynamic” setting within
the “mappings” key.
Let’s set it to “false.”
Let’s run the query to add the index again.
Let’s now see what happens when we index
a document containing an additional field
compared to the mapping.
The document is indexed just fine.
That’s probably not what you expected.
Didn’t we just disable dynamic mapping?
Well, let’s try to retrieve the mapping
and see what is going on.
We still only see a mapping for the “first_name”
field, so something is different this time.
To check what is going on, let’s write a
simple search query which searches the “first_name” field.
Within the results, we can see that the document
was indexed just fine and that it contains
both of the fields that we specified.
Let’s make a copy of the search request
and search the “last_name” field instead.
The document no longer matches our query.
Alright, so here is the explanation.
Setting the “dynamic” setting to “false”
instructs Elasticsearch to ignore new fields.
Notice how I said “ignore” and not “reject.”
What happens is that the field is still part
of the “_source” object as you saw, but
it is not indexed.
Remember that the “_source” object does
not represent the data structure that Elasticsearch
uses to perform searches.
The “last_name” field is therefore left
out of that data structure, being an inverted
index since we are dealing with a string value.
That’s why we see the field within the “_source”
object, but we are unable to use the field
within our queries.
We don’t get an error if we try to do so,
because leaving fields out when indexing documents
is perfectly valid, which you saw a bit earlier.
The value not being indexed is actually a
consequence of no field mapping being added,
since we cannot index fields that do not have
a mapping.
When dynamic mapping is enabled, a mapping
is created automatically before indexing field values.
In this example we disabled that behavior,
causing the value to not be indexed.
When the “dynamic” setting is set to “false,”
new fields must be mapped explicitly if we
want the field values to be indexed and thereby
searchable.
While this behavior does have its uses, I
generally don’t recommend it.
There is a third possible value for the “dynamic”
setting besides “true” and “false.”
By specifying a string with a value of “strict,”
Elasticsearch will reject any document that
contains an unmapped field.
To index a document, all of its fields must
therefore be mapped explicitly.
This behavior is similar to a relational database
schema, for instance.
Let’s delete the index and set dynamic mapping
to “strict.”
Running the index query again, we should get
an error.
Indeed we get an error stating that the “last_name”
field is not allowed because the “dynamic”
setting is set to “strict.”
Inheritance is actually supported for the
“dynamic” setting, which gives you fine
grained control of dynamic mapping.
Suppose that we are indexing computers.
We set dynamic mapping to “strict” at
the index level, because we want to be in
full control of the mapping.
All of the fields within the index inherit
this configuration.
At the top level, this means that both the
“name” and “specifications” fields
inherit the “dynamic” setting with a value
of “strict.”
The inheritance works on multiple levels,
so the nested “cpu” and “other” fields
inherit the setting from its parent field,
being the “specifications” field.
Since the “cpu” field has inherited strict mapping, we can only provide a “name”  field for this object.
The index query on your screen therefore fails because there is no mapping for the “frequency” field.
Remember that strict dynamic mapping doesn’t
change the fact that we can leave out fields
when indexing documents; fields may always
contain zero or more values regardless of
how dynamic mapping is configured.
The “other” field stores many different
fields depending on the product, so we cannot
map all of the possible fields in advance.
Instead, we can enable dynamic mapping for
just that particular field, overriding the
inherited value.
Since the “other” field is an object,
its properties will inherit this configuration,
enabling us to add new fields dynamically.
In this example, we can add a “security”
field just fine.
Alright, two more things to cover in this
lecture; numeric detection and date detection.
To save a bit of time, I will just be showing
these on a couple of diagrams.
As always, the queries are available within the GitHub repository in case you want to run them.
First, enabling numeric detection is just
a matter of setting the “numeric_detection”
setting to “true” at the root level of
the “mappings” object — exactly as we
did with the “dynamic” setting.
When numeric detection is enabled, Elasticsearch
will check the contents of strings to see
if they contain only numeric values.
If that is the case, the data type of a field
will be set to either “float” or “long”
when mapped through dynamic mapping.
Finally, let’s talk about date detection.
By default, Elasticsearch inspects string
values to look for dates in the following formats.
If there is a match, Elasticsearch will create
a “date” field, provided that the field
hasn’t been seen before, and that dynamic
mapping is enabled.
The field is created using the default date
format.
You can disable date detection altogether
by setting the “date_detection” setting
to “false.”
You can also configure the dynamic date formats
that are recognized.
This may be useful if you have applications sending dates to Elasticsearch in non-standard formats.
Those were the basic — and probably most common — ways in which you can configure dynamic mapping.
There is another way, though, which we will
take a look at in the next lecture.