Another way in which we can configure dynamic
mapping is by using so-called dynamic templates.
A dynamic template consists of one or more
conditions along with the mapping a field
should use if it matches the conditions.
Dynamic templates are used when dynamic mapping
is enabled and a new field is encountered
without any existing mapping.
Let’s get straight to business so you can
see what I mean.
I have a partial query prepared, which will
add a new throwaway index.
Dynamic templates are added within a key named
“dynamic_templates,” nested within the “mappings” key.
Each dynamic template should be an object
within this array, so let’s add an empty object.
Within this object we add a key with the name of the dynamic template, which can be anything we want.
Its value should be an object.
I will name the template “integers.”
You will see why in a moment.
The first thing we need to do is to define when this template should kick in, i.e. a match condition.
As you will see in a moment, there are several
ways of doing this, but let’s begin with
the simplest one; matching based on the detected
data type.
I will quickly type that out and explain it
afterwards.
We are not done yet, but let’s take a moment
to talk about this parameter.
The “match_mapping_type” parameter is
used to match a given JSON data type.
On your screen you can see a table listing
JSON data types and which value should be
used for the parameter within the dynamic
template.
It’s important to note that the values to
the right are not the data types that fields
will be mapped as; we will define those in
a moment.
It’s also worth noting that “double”
is used for numbers with a decimal, since
there is no way of distinguishing a “double”
from a “float” in JSON.
Likewise, we also cannot distinguish between
an “integer” and a “long.”
As a result, the wider data type will always
be chosen.
If we go back to the query that we are working
on, we set the match type to “long,” meaning
that the template will be applied to whole
numbers.
We still haven’t defined what should happen
if the condition matches, so let’s do that now.
What we have to do is to define a field mapping
that should be used if our condition matches.
This is done within a “mapping” parameter,
which should be in the same format as the
field mappings you have previously seen.
This means that we can define the data type
that should be used, so let’s do that.
That’s the most basic structure of a dynamic
template.
We defined a condition that evaluates to true
if the detected JSON data type is “long,”
in which case the field mapping will be as
specified.
In this example, this means that dynamic field
mappings will not use the “long” data
type as would otherwise be the default behavior,
but the “integer” data type instead.
If we wanted to, we could add mapping parameters
to the field mapping as well, but let’s
keep things simple for now.
Let’s run the query to create the index.
Let’s now index a simple document with a
field that matches the condition that we defined.
By default, this new field would be mapped
as a “long” field, so if everything works
as intended, we should see it being mapped
as an “integer” instead.
Let’s inspect the mapping and take a look.
Indeed we can see that the field was mapped
as an “integer,” so the dynamic template
worked as intended.
If you don’t want to just take my word for
it, you can of course test the difference
with and without the template.
Another example of a dynamic template could
be to adjust how strings are mapped.
As you know, they are mapped as both a “text”
mapping and a “keyword” mapping by default.
That might be what you want, but it could
also be the case that you only want one of them.
Or perhaps you want to change the value of
the “ignore_above” parameter or get rid
of it altogether.
Whatever the case, that would be a good use
of a dynamic template.
The example you see on your screen now shows
how string values can be mapped according
to the default rules, with the exception that
the “ignore_above” parameter now contains
a value of 512 instead of 256.
That’s probably of limited use, but hopefully
you get the point of how the default mapping
rules can be tweaked to fit your needs.
Let’s now move on to slightly more advanced
dynamic templates.
I don’t want to spend a lot of time typing
out the queries, so I will just show them
on some slides and explain what they do.
As always, you can find the queries within
the GitHub repository if you want to run them.
Besides simply matching based on the detected
JSON data type, we have a number of other
options available, so let’s go through them
one by one.
First up, we have the “match” and “unmatch”
parameters.
These parameters enable us to specify conditions
for the name of the field being evaluated.
The “match” parameter is used to specify
a pattern that the field name must match.
The “unmatch” parameter can then be used
to specify a pattern that excludes certain
fields that are matched by the “match”
parameter.
I hope that makes sense.
Otherwise you will see an example in a moment.
Notice how I mentioned the word “pattern”
a couple of times for both of the parameters.
That’s because both of them support wildcards
with the asterisk symbol.
This makes sense, because hard coding specific
field names into dynamic templates probably
doesn’t make much sense.
Let’s take a look at an example of how these
parameters can be used.
The first thing to notice is how this example
actually includes two dynamic templates.
In situations where there are more than one,
the templates are processed in order, and
the first matching template wins.
The first template matches fields where the
name begins with the string “text” and an underscore.
The “unmatch” parameter then filters out fields that end with an underscore and the string “keyword.”
What this template does is therefore to map
string values to “text” fields — provided
that the field name matches the pattern defined
by the “match” parameter and doesn’t
match the pattern defined by the “unmatch”
parameter.
Fields names that end with an underscore followed
by the string “keyword” are caught by
the second template that maps them as “keyword”
fields.
This means that if we run this query… we
will get this mapping.
The description field matched the first template,
whereas the product ID field matched the second.
Did you notice how both of the templates included
the “match_mapping_type” parameter as well?
That’s because we can include more than
one condition within a dynamic template; the
parameters that you have seen — and will
see — can all be combined to form a set
of match conditions, so you are not limited
to just one.
Using the “match” and “unmatch” parameters
is useful for using naming conventions as
a way of applying field mappings.
If we need more flexibility than what the
“match” parameter provides with wildcards,
we can set a parameter named “match_pattern”
to “regex.”
What this does, is to adjust the behavior of the “match” parameter to support regular expressions.
In this case the regular expression matches
strings that end with “_name.”
Adding a document with these three field names...
will therefore create the following mapping.
This approach is useful in situations where
simple wildcards are not enough and you need
the flexibility of regular expressions.
Very similar to the “match” and “unmatch”
parameters, we have the “path_match” and
“path_unmatch” parameters.
The difference is that these parameters match
the full field path, instead of just the field name itself.
To be clear, by “full path” I am referring
to the dotted path.
For instance, you might have a “name”
object containing a “first_name” key,
in which case the path would be “name.first_name.”
We can also use wildcards within these paths.
Let’s look at an example.
Here we use the “path_match” parameter
to match any name part.
The “name” object will contain three keys;
“first_name,” “middle_name,” and “last_name.”
The wildcard matches all of these.
I haven’t added the “path_unmatch” parameter,
but it behaves the same as the “unmatch”
parameter, except that it considers the field
path.
What I have added, though, is the “copy_to”
mapping parameter, which copies values into
the specified field.
In this case it enables us to query the full
name as a single field, instead of having
to query three different fields.
Adding the following document... will therefore
cause the following mapping to be created.
A mapping will also be created for the “full_name”
field, but I have omitted it from this diagram.
It will be created using the default dynamic
mapping rule for string values, meaning that
it will be mapped as both a “text” and
“keyword” field.
Just one thing left to cover before we are
done.
Within the “mapping” key of a dynamic
template, you can make use of two placeholders.
The first one is named “dynamic_type,”
which you can see in use on your screen.
We can use placeholders within string values by enclosing the placeholder name within curly brackets.
The “dynamic_type” placeholder is replaced with the data type that was detected by dynamic mapping.
This template matches all data types and adds
a mapping of that same data type.
If we didn’t have this placeholder at our
disposal, we would have to add a dynamic template
for each data type, which would be quite inconvenient.
The purpose of this template is to set the
“index” parameter to “false.”
The data type is going to be the same as it
otherwise would be with dynamic mapping.
This particular example with disabling indexing
could be used for time series data.
Perhaps you recall me mentioning that this
is a common optimization for time series data
where you typically don’t need to filter
on specific values, but rather aggregate by
time intervals.
Another optimization for time series data
is to disable norms, which you can do in exactly
the same way.
Anyway, let’s check the mapping that is
created when adding the following document.
As you can see, both field mappings have the
“index” parameter set to “false” as we expected.
Before ending this lecture, I want to briefly
talk about the differences between dynamic
templates and index templates, just in case
you are confused.
An index template applies field mappings and/or
index settings when its pattern matches the
name of an index.
A dynamic template, on the other hand, is
applied when a new field is encountered and
dynamic mapping is enabled.
If the template’s conditions match, the
field mapping is added for the new field.
A dynamic template is therefore a way to dynamically
add mappings for fields that match certain
criteria, where an index template adds a fixed
set of field mappings.