Before we get back to analyzers, I want to
give a couple of recommendations in regards
to mapping.
Some of them are my own personal opinions,
so whether or not you want to follow them
is of course totally up to you.
First and foremost, I recommend that you make use
of explicit mapping - at least for production clusters.
Dynamic mapping is convenient during development,
but the generated field mappings are often
not the most efficient ones.
If you intend to store a high number of documents,
you can typically save a lot of disk space
with more optimized mappings, for instance.
By using explicit mappings, I mean to set
the “dynamic” parameter to “strict”
and not just “false.”
Setting it to “false” will enable you
to add fields for which there are no mappings.
The fields are then simply ignored in terms
of indexing.
Querying such fields won’t match anything,
which might lead to unexpected search results.
That’s why I recommend that you set the
“dynamic” parameter to “strict,” because
then you cannot end up in a situation like
that.
Using strict mapping essentially means that
you are always in control.
Another related recommendation is to not always
map “text” fields as both “text” and
“keyword” unless you need to do so.
This happens with dynamic mapping by default,
but it is often not necessary and just takes
up additional disk space.
If you disable dynamic mapping, you should
ask yourself how you intend to query a given field.
Do you want to perform full-text searches
on it?
Then you should add a “text” mapping.
Do you want to use the field for aggregations,
sorting, or filtering based on exact values?
Then you should add a “keyword” mapping.
If you want to do both, you should map the
field in both ways, but that is typically
not necessary.
If you have full control of whichever application
is sending data to Elasticsearch, then I recommend
that you disable coercion as well.
Type coercion is convenient, but it is essentially
a way for Elasticsearch to forgive you for
not doing the right thing.
Whenever possible, always provide the correct
data types in the JSON objects that you send
to Elasticsearch.
If you add explicit field mappings for numeric
fields, then you should consider which kind
of numbers you will index.
Sometimes it is not necessary to map a field
as “long,” because an “integer” might be enough.
The former data type can hold larger numbers,
but also requires more disk space.
Likewise, “double” requires twice as much
disk space as “float,” so if you don’t
need really high precision, then you should
be fine using “float.”
There are a number of mapping parameters that
you can use to limit the amount of data that
Elasticsearch stores.
Actually it’s Apache Lucene that stores
this data, but that’s besides the point.
We already discussed them, so this is just
a quick reminder.
If you know that you won’t use a field for
sorting, aggregations, and scripting, you
can set “doc_values” to “false” and
save quite a bit of disk space.
If you won’t use a field for relevance scoring,
then you can set “norms” to “false”
to avoid storing data that is only used for
relevance scoring.
Lastly, if you won’t use a field for filtering,
you can disable indexing by setting “index”
to “false.”
The field can still be used for aggregations, so this
is a common thing to do for time series data.
These parameters are useful when storing lots
of documents, and the savings can be significant.
If you only need to store a low number of
documents, then it’s probably not worth
the effort to deal with these parameters;
the savings would be limited, and you might
be overcomplicating things.
There is no rule as to when it’s worth it
to use these parameters and when it isn’t.
As a rule of thumb, though, it’s probably
not worth it for less than a million documents.
If you know that you will need to store many
million documents when defining your mappings,
then you should optimize the mappings from
the beginning.
That way you won’t need to reindex documents
into a new index later on.
If you don’t do it from the beginning, the
worst that can really happen is that you will
need to reindex documents sometime, so it’s
really not the end of the world.
There are more optimizations that you can
do depending on your use case, but these are
the most common ones.
I don’t want to go into a lot of detail
and bore you with edge case optimizations,
so these are my general recommendations when
it comes to mapping fields.