Let’s get back to text analysis now and
talk about two important concepts; stemming
and stop words.
Consider the following sentence.
“Loved” is in the past tense.
“Drinking” is a gerund.
“Bottles” is the plural form of the word
“bottle.”
“Year’s” indicates possession.
Those were just a couple of linguistic details
of the sentence.
The point is that those words are not in their
root form.
Suppose that we index a document with this
sentence into an Elasticsearch index, using
the “standard” analyzer, which is the
default behavior for “text” fields.
All the analyzer is going to do is to lowercase
all of the letters and get rid of the punctuation
— apart from tokenizing the sentence of
course.
What happens if we search for the term “loves?”
The document is not going to match because
the indexed word is in a different tense.
That’s typically not ideal because the meaning
is essentially the same regardless of which
tense the word is in; the tense being different
doesn’t mean that the document is not relevant.
In fact, we probably want the document to
match the query instead of getting no results
and requiring users to search in exactly the
correct tense.
We can fix this by using something called
stemming.
Stemming is the process of reducing words
to their root form.
For example, the word “loved” can be stemmed
to “love,” and “drinking” can be stemmed
to “drink.”
Let’s try to apply stemming on the whole
sentence and see what it then looks like.
As you can see, not all words are stemmed
to valid words, depending on how aggressive
the stemming is configured to be.
That’s just how stemming algorithms work,
so that’s nothing to be concerned about.
Stemming is just something Elasticsearch uses
internally, so no one is going to actually
see these terms.
I will get back to how stemming works in the
context of search queries very soon, but let’s
talk about the concept of stop words first.
Simply put, stop words are words that are
filtered out in the analysis process.
That can be any words, but stop words almost
always refer to the most common words in a
given language.
A couple of examples are the words “a,”
“the,” “at,” “of,” and “on.”
Common to all of these words is that they
provide little to no value in terms of relevance.
Consider a search on Google, for instance.
It’s quite unlikely that any of these words
are going to affect a web page’s relevance
to your query.
They are of course important words in the
English language, but they provide little
to no value in the context of relevance scoring.
As a result, it’s a fairly common approach
to remove these words during text processing.
Doing so used to be more popular than it is
today, at least in the context of Elasticsearch.
The reason is that the relevance algorithm
that is used by Elasticsearch has become much
better at limiting how much stop words influence
search results.
That’s why I generally don’t recommend
that you remove stop words.
It is also not the default behavior, as the
“standard” analyzer does not remove them.
That being said, let’s see how removing
stop words would affect the sentence from
before.
As you can see, the words “of” and “on”
would be removed.
Now that you know what stemming and stop words
are, let’s see how analyzers are used when
searching for documents.