I told you how analyzers are used when indexing
“text” fields.
That’s only half the story though, as they
are also used for search queries.
I might be getting ahead of myself, because
we haven’t gotten to search queries yet.
However, you might be wondering how we can
search for the values that we index if they
are changed during the analysis process.
Perhaps I got you confused in the previous
lecture when we discussed stemming and stop
words, so let me clear up any doubts that
you may have.
Let’s take the example from the previous
lecture and run it through a custom analyzer.
The analyzer behaves the same as the “standard”
analyzer, except that it also stems words.
On the diagram, you can see how the sentence
was analyzed.
In particular, the terms were lowercased,
some words were stemmed, and the period symbol
was removed as well.
That’s great, but what is going to happen
if we search for the word “drinking?”
When indexing the document, the word “drinking”
was stemmed to its root form, so will the
document match the query?
Yes, it will.
That’s because the search query is analyzed
in the same way as when indexing the field value.
Let me illustrate that on a diagram.
So when the document is indexed, Elasticsearch
inspects the mapping for the “description” field.
It detects that it’s a “text” field,
which means that it should be analyzed.
It then checks if an analyzer is configured
for the field.
If so, that analyzer is used, and otherwise
the “standard” analyzer is used.
In this example a custom analyzer named “stemming_analyzer”
is configured for the field, so that one is
used in favor of the “standard” analyzer.
It pretty much behaves as the “standard”
analyzer with the exception that words for
the English language are stemmed.
The result of running the text through this analyzer
is the same as what you saw a moment ago.
Those were the terms that were indexed and
stored within the inverted index.
Remember that the original field value is
still available within the “_source” object,
but that is not what search queries are run
against.
Elasticsearch now receives our search query.
It looks at which fields we are searching,
which is the “description” field in this example.
It then does the same thing as when the field
value was indexed; it runs the value through
the analyzer that is configured in the field
mapping.
That is, it analyzes the value that we are
searching for.
The word “drinking” is therefore stemmed
by the analyzer, resulting in the term “drink.”
This matches what is stored within the field’s
inverted index, and so the document matches
the query.
As you can see, the same analyzer is used
both when indexing documents and at search time.
If this were not the case, you would
get unpredictable search results.
This is also why queries run against “text”
fields are case insensitive by default.
If your query takes the input from a website,
it might happen that someone enters a query
in all capitalized letters.
That’s not an issue because the string will be lowercased at search time by the “standard” analyzer.
If a custom analyzer is used, this only happens
when it includes the “lowercase” token filter.
The point is that the query is analyzed in the same way as the field values that were indexed.
It’s possible to change this behavior and
specify a different analyzer, but that is
rarely needed, so I won’t cover that in
this course.
If you do need to do so, you should be very
careful, because if you don’t do it right,
you might be in for a world of trouble.
Anyway, hopefully that clears up some potential
confusion as to how values can be matched
even though they differ from the ones specified
within search queries.