In the previous lecture you learned the very
basics of analysis in Elasticsearch, and in
particular the “standard” analyzer.
You saw an example of how a string is analyzed
by default.
There is actually a very convenient API that
you can use to test how Elasticsearch analyzes
a given string.
This is useful in a couple of scenarios, such
as for building custom analyzers, and — as
in this case — experimenting to better understand
what happens as part of the analysis process.
Let’s write a query to test the “standard”
analyzer.
So the endpoint is “_analyze,” and the
HTTP verb should be POST.
We supply the text that we want to be analyzed
within a parameter named “text.”
As
for the text, I will just paste in a really
lame joke, so my apologies for the poor sense
of humor! ;-)
I know, it’s not even funny.
Anyway, it will work just fine for us.
If we were to run the query now, the text
would be analyzed with the “standard” analyzer.
That’s actually what we want, but let’s
just specify this explicitly with the “analyzer” parameter.
In place of “standard,” we can write the
name of other built-in analyzers or custom ones.
Let’s run the query and inspect the result.
The result contains the tokens that were emitted
by the analyzer.
Apart from the token itself, each token also
contains some metadata, most of which I briefly
mentioned in the previous lecture.
Among this metadata is a type, which will
usually be alphanumeric.
In our case, the text included a number, and
so the first token is of the numeric type.
We can also see the start and end offsets
for each token.
These are the character offsets for where the token appeared in the text before it was analyzed.
Alright, so we can see that our text has been
tokenized at word boundaries.
It might look like the tokenization was done
based on whitespaces, but that is not the
case, because the algorithm is a bit more
advanced than that.
For instance, if we were to remove the whitespace
between the three periods and the word “ducks,”
we would still end up with two tokens being
“third” and “ducks.”
The “standard” tokenizer also takes care
of removing most symbols, such as commas,
exclamation marks, periods, etc.
That’s because these provide no value when
performing full-text searches.
It also trims whitespaces, so the triple whitespace
that’s part of our text is just ignored.
Looking at the last token, we can see that
the “lowercase” token filter has also
been at work, since the word “ducks” is
no longer in uppercase letters.
There is really nothing new here, as all of
this is just a practical way of showing you
what you learned in the previous lecture.
Instead of specifying an analyzer, we can
also specify the parts making up an analyzer,
being character filters, a tokenizer, and
token filters.
Let’s replicate the “standard” analyzer
by specifying its components explicitly, just
to show you that the result is the same.
I will just make a copy of the existing query
and remove the “analyzer” parameter.
First, let’s add a parameter named “char_filter,”
of course being where we define any character filters.
Since the “standard” analyzer doesn’t
make use of any character filters, I will
just leave the array empty.
I could have left out the parameter entirely
as the behavior would be the same, but let’s
just be explicit.
Next, let’s add the “standard” tokenizer
with the “tokenizer” parameter.
The last thing we need to do, is to specify
the “lowercase” token filter.
We do that with a parameter named “filter.”
That’s it!
That’s essentially all the “standard”
analyzer does.
Scrolling through the results, we can see
that the result is the same as before.
When we get to building custom analyzers,
keep this API in mind, because it is super
useful for testing things out before applying
them to documents.
That’s it for this lecture.
In the next one, we will take a look at what actually happens with the tokens that an analyzer yields.