You should now have a good understanding of
how analyzers work and when they are used.
Elasticsearch comes with a number of built-in
analyzers.
These are simply pre-configured combinations
of character filters, token filters, and a tokenizer.
They are available for your convenience, so
there is nothing magical about them; you can
make custom analyzers that do the same thing
if you want to.
Let’s quickly go through the most important
ones.
First, we have the “standard” analyzer,
which we have already talked about.
It splits text into terms at word boundaries,
and also removes punctuation in the process.
That’s done with the “standard” tokenizer.
Apart from that, it also lowercases letters
with the “lowercase” token filter.
It actually contains the “stop” token
filter as well, for removing stop words.
This filter is disabled by default, but can
be enabled through configuration, which you
will see in a moment.
The “simple” analyzer is quite similar
to the “standard” analyzer.
The difference is that it splits the input
text whenever it encounters anything other
than a letter, where the “standard” analyzer
splits by word.
This analyzer also lowercases terms, but this
is done by the “lowercase” tokenizer and
not a token filter.
That’s pretty unusual because a tokenizer
is not really supposed to do that.
This is a performance hack to avoid passing
through the input twice.
The “whitespace” analyzer simply splits
the input text whenever it encounters a whitespace.
Unlike the other analyzers, it does not lowercase
letters.
The “keyword” analyzer is a no-op analyzer,
meaning that it leaves the input text intact
and simply outputs it as a single term.
Sounds familiar?
This analyzer is actually used for fields
of the “keyword” data type by default.
Remember how these fields are used for matching
exact values?
Behind the scenes, the “keyword” analyzer
is used, and the exact input values are stored
within inverted indices.
The “pattern” analyzer lets you define
a regular expression to match token separators.
This essentially means that you should match
whatever should cause the input text to be
split into tokens.
This can be anything you want, really, so
this analyzer provides a lot of flexibility.
The default pattern matches all non-word characters
as shown in the example.
Note that the analyzer lowercases letters
by default, but this can be disabled.
Last but not least, there are a number of
language specific analyzers.
Let’s head over to the documentation for
a moment.
This page shows a list of the built-in analyzers,
most of which we just covered.
Let’s click the link to the documentation
for the language analyzers.
At the top of the page, we can see a list of the
available analyzers, covering most languages.
Let’s click the “english” one and see
what it does.
This takes us to a query snippet showing how the analyzer could be implemented as a custom analyzer.
That’s not how you would use the analyzer,
unless you want to change things.
This just shows us the pieces the analyzer
consists of so that we can understand what
it does.
As we can see, it uses the “standard”
tokenizer and a number of token filters.
The first one is a so-called possessive stemmer,
which removes possession from words.
Possession typically refers to ‘s, as in
“Peter’s dog.”
It then lowercases all letters as most analyzers
do and also removes English stop words.
The “keyword_marker” filter is a way to
exclude words from stemming, but it is not
enabled by default, so let’s ignore that
one.
Finally the analyzer stems words for the English
language.
While this example is specific to the English
language, this is more or less what most of
the analyzers look like.
Some of the analyzers do handle some language
specific quirks, though.
As you can see, the language analyzers are
just standard implementations that handle
basic things.
They are often a good starting point if you
don’t need anything super advanced.
Sometimes you might want to expand the configuration
though.
An example could be to handle synonyms, which
is a topic that is covered later in the course.
Those were the most interesting built-in analyzers.
Let’s now look at how we can use them within
field mappings.
That’s actually extremely easy, because
all we need to do is to specify the name of
an analyzer for a mapping parameter named
“analyzer.”
The following query shows how the “english” language analyzer can be specified for a “description” field.
This analyzer is used both at index and search
time.
Pretty easy, right?
While all of the built-in analyzers can be
used in this way, many of them can also be
configured to adjust their behavior.
For instance, the “standard” analyzer
can easily be configured to remove stop words,
which it doesn’t do by default.
Instead of having to implement a custom analyzer
from scratch, we can configure the built-in analyzer.
That’s exactly what you see on your screen now.
We are actually creating a custom analyzer
by extending the “standard” analyzer,
as specified within the “type” parameter.
In this example, I have given it a name of
“remove_english_stop_words,” but that’s
just an arbitrary name.
The structure of the query is a bit different
compared to what you have seen so far, but
don’t worry about that for now; I will cover
that in detail in the next lecture.
For now, let’s focus on the innermost object.
Besides specifying the type of analyzer, we
simply add any parameters to this object.
So which ones are available, then?
We can check that within the documentation
for each analyzer.
Let’s head back to the browser and go to
the documentation for the “standard” analyzer.
If we scroll down a bit, we can see which
parameters the analyzer supports.
In the example you saw a moment ago, I used
the “stopwords” parameter, which we also see here.
Okay, so now that we have created a custom
analyzer, how do we use it?
You probably won’t be surprised that we
use it in the exact same way as you saw earlier;
by simply specifying its name.
That’s it for built-in analyzers!
Now it’s time to create a custom analyzer.