Sometimes you might have an existing analyzer
that you want to update.
As with mapping, you should try to get it
right the first time to save yourself from
some additional work, but things change sometimes.
In this lecture, I am going to show you how
to update an existing analyzer.
For that purpose I have prepared a number
of queries in advance, because you have seen
them all before.
We have an index with a custom analyzer, but
we haven’t used it within a field mapping
yet, so let’s do that first.
Particularly, let’s add a “description”
field that uses the analyzer named “my_custom_analyzer.”
An index is not much fun without any documents
in it, so let’s index a document.
Next, I have a fairly simple search query
that searches the “description” field
for the term “that.”
There is one unusual thing about this query,
though; it specifies an analyzer.
By default, the analyzer from the “description”
field’s mapping would be used to analyze
the query, being the analyzer named “my_custom_analyzer.”
Analyzing the query with this particular analyzer,
would remove the word “that” from the
query, causing us to essentially search for
nothing.
That’s because the analyzer is configured
to remove stop words.
This default behavior is overridden when specifying
the “analyzer” parameter.
The “keyword” analyzer is then used instead,
which essentially means that the search query
will be left intact.
Our example document was indexed using the
custom analyzer, and so stop words were removed.
The term “that” therefore doesn’t appear
within the inverted index for the “description”field.
You can see the inverted index to the right.
So what’s the point of this?
Specifying the “keyword” analyzer is a
trick to avoid removing stop words from the
query, because we actually want to know if
the document contains the term “that.”
You will see why in a moment.
Sorry if this got a bit confusing, but hopefully
it will all make sense in a moment.
If we run the query, we should see that no
documents are matched.
That’s because we are searching for the
term “that,” which is a stop word, and
hence it was removed when indexing the document.
In other words, that’s to be expected.
Let’s now actually get to updating the analyzer.
We do that with the Update Index Settings
API as you have already seen.
We just specify the full analyzer as if it
didn’t already exist.
In the query that you see on your screen,
I have removed the “stop” token filter,
because I no longer want to remove stop words.
As when adding a new analyzer to an index,
we need to close the index before we can modify
the analyzer.
Now that the index has been closed, we are
ready to update the analyzer.
That was the only modification we needed to
do, so let’s reopen the index.
Just to prove to you that the analyzer has
indeed been updated, let’s quickly retrieve
the index’ settings.
Indeed we can see that the analyzer no longer
contains the “stop” token filter.
Let’s now index another document with the
same value as the first one, so I will just
run the same query again.
Running the search query again should give
us a different result compared to the first
time we ran it.
This time around one document is matched,
being the one we just indexed.
What happened was that the second document
was indexed with the updated analyzer which
did not remove any stop words.
As a result, the inverted index for the “description”
field does contain the term “that,” unlike
for the first document.
Hopefully that makes sense, but it also raises
a red flag.
Our index now contains documents that were
analyzed in two different ways, which can
lead to a number of issues.
Search queries will use the latest version
of the analyzer by default, but some documents
were analyzed using the old version.
That can lead to quite unpredictable search
results.
In this example, two documents contain the
same value for the “description” field
within the “_source” object, but only
one matches the query.
That’s probably not what you would expect
if you were unaware that the analyzer had
been changed after indexing documents.
We therefore need to handle this to avoid
causing ourselves some massive headaches.
We could reindex documents into a new index,
causing them to be analyzed with the new analyzer.
There is a simpler approach, though; using
the Update By Query API, which you hopefully
remember from earlier in the course.
Besides updating documents with a script,
this API can actually be used for a different
purpose as well; reindexing values.
That’s what we need in this case, because
we want the first document to be reindexed
with the updated analyzer in place.
We can simply do that with the last query
that I have prepared.
It reindexes all documents since no “query”
parameter is specified.
It’s possible to limit the scope of the
query to specific documents, but we don’t
do that now.
Let’s run the query.
The results state that two documents were
updated.
Let’s now run the search query again.
And there we go!
Both documents now match the query, because
the first document that we indexed has now
been analyzed using the updated analyzer.
Apart from simply updating an analyzer, we
took a quick detour to also discover a potential
problem with doing so.
I wanted to show you that, because if we are
not careful, updating analyzers can cause
us all kinds of trouble.
Always try to get your analyzers right the
first time, i.e. before indexing documents.
Sometimes it is perfectly valid to have to
change the configuration of an analyzer, though.
You just need to handle the situation appropriately
and everything should be fine.