Alright, now that you know the basics of text
analysis in Elasticsearch, let’s take a
look at what actually happens with the result,
being the tokens.
A couple of different data structures are
used to store field values.
The data structure that is used for a field
depends on its data type.
The reason Elasticsearch uses more than one
data structure, is to ensure efficient data
retrieval for different access patterns.
For example, searching for a given term is
handled differently than aggregating data.
Actually these data structures are all handled
by Apache Lucene and not Elasticsearch.
I will get back to some of the data structures
later, because I want to focus on one in this
lecture; namely one called an inverted index.
An inverted index is essentially a mapping
between terms and which documents contain them.
Note that by “term,” I am referring to
the tokens that are emitted by the analyzer.
Generally speaking, the “token” terminology
is only used in the context of analyzers,
so you will mostly hear me say “terms.”
Anyway, let’s take the example from the
previous lecture and see how that would be
stored within an inverted index.
As you can see, each unique term is placed
in the index together with information about
which documents contain the term.
This is stored as document IDs internally
but illustrated differently on the diagram
for simplicity.
Notice how the terms are sorted alphabetically.
This example is for an index with a single
document, so that’s of course not very exciting,
as each term only appears in one document.
Let’s index a couple of more documents into
it and see what the inverted index then looks like.
This made the inverted index just slightly
more interesting.
If you want to have a closer look at it, then
I encourage you to pause the video for a moment.
I’m sure you can imagine how this index
would grow as more documents are indexed.
What makes an inverted index so powerful is
how efficient it is to look up a term and
find the documents in which the term appears.
Suppose that we perform a search for the term
“ducks.”
Figuring out which documents contain that
term is just a matter of performing a simple
lookup in the inverted index.
Doing that, we can see that documents #1 and
#3 contain the term.
That makes the process of searching for a
term super simple and efficient.
Simple stuff, right?
The reason the index is called an inverted
index is just that the more logical mapping
would be to have a mapping from documents
to the terms they contain, i.e. the other
way around.
That doesn’t provide the fast lookups that
we need, so that’s why the relationship
is inverted.
That’s all there is to the terminology,
so it sounds more fancy than it really is.
It should be said, though, that the inverted
index you saw was a slight simplification.
The inverted indices that are stored within
Apache Lucene contain a bit more information,
such as data that is used for relevance scoring.
As you can imagine, we don’t just want to
get the documents back that contain a given
term; we also want them to be ranked by how
well they match.
That’s a topic for later in the course,
so we will get to that.
Now you know the basics of what an inverted
index is.
The examples that I showed you were just for
a couple of sentences assumed to belong to
the same field.
What happens if we index documents containing
a number of different fields as you see on
your screen now?
Are all the values stored within the same
inverted index, or what happens?
An inverted index is actually created for
each text field, meaning that we will have
two inverted indices in this example; one
for the “name” field, and one for the
“description” field.
The text is analyzed and stored in the same
way as you just saw, so the key thing here
is to understand that an inverted index exists
within the scope of a field.
You can see the two inverted indices that
would be created on your screen now.
Go ahead and pause the video if you want to
take a closer look at it.
But why did I say that there will be one inverted
index per text field?
That’s because fields with other data types
use different data structures.
For example, numeric, date, and geospatial
fields are all stored as BKD trees, because
this data structure is very efficient for
geospatial and numeric range queries.
Dates are included because dates are actually
stored as “long” values internally, but
I will get back to that in a couple of lectures.
Alright, let’s take a short moment to recap
on what we covered in this lecture, because
it’s super important.
When text fields are analyzed, the resulting
terms are placed into an inverted index.
This happens for every “text” field, so
each field has a dedicated inverted index.
An inverted index is a sorted mapping of the
unique terms from all documents containing
a value for a given field, to which documents
contain those terms.
Inverted indices are created and maintained
by Apache Lucene, which Elasticsearch builds
on top of.
Having an inverted index, it is super efficient
to run a query that asks the question: “Which
documents contain the term X?”
An inverted index contains more information
than this mapping, but we will get to that
later in the course.
Inverted indices is one of the data structures
that Elasticsearch uses, but other data structures
are used as well.
For example, numeric values and geospatial
data is stored within BKD trees.
We will get to some of the data structures
later in the course, but for now the important
thing is to understand the basics of what
an inverted index is.