Now that you know the basics of text analysis
and how the resulting terms are stored, let’s
move on to talking about mapping.
We will revisit the concept of analysis, because
as you will soon find out, mapping and analysis
are quite closely related.
So what is mapping all about?
Mapping defines the structure of documents
and how they are indexed and stored.
This includes the fields of a document and
their data types.
As a simplification, you can think of it as the equivalent of a table schema in a relational database.
On your screen, you can see how a simple table in a relational database could be mapped in Elasticsearch.
There is more to Elasticsearch mapping than
this, so this is just a way for you to wrap
your head around the general idea of what
mapping is.
Simply defining the fields and their data
types is not that exciting, so luckily there
is much more to it than that.
Mapping is actually pretty cool and not quite
as boring as it sounds.
In Elasticsearch, there are two basic approaches
to mapping; explicit and dynamic mapping.
With explicit mapping, we define fields and
their data types ourselves, typically when
creating an index.
That’s exactly what you saw on the diagram
a moment ago.
To make Elasticsearch easier to use, a field
mapping will automatically be created when
Elasticsearch encounters a new field.
It will inspect the supplied field value to
figure out how the field should be mapped.
If you supply a string value, for instance,
Elasticsearch will use the “text” data
type for the mapping.
As you will see, explicit and dynamic mapping
can actually be combined, so mapping is quite
flexible in Elasticsearch.
Anyway, let’s get started!