Before we really get into mapping, I want to quickly give you an overview of the available data types.
There are quite a few of them, so I will just
highlight the most important ones.
On your screen, you can see some of the basic
Elasticsearch data types.
You probably recognize some of them from various
programming languages, | but either way, their
uses should be pretty obvious.
Apart from these, there are a number of more
specialized data types, such as an “ip”
data type for storing IP addresses.
Some of the specialized data types are related
to specific Elasticsearch features, such as
for auto-completion or geospatial searches.
Instead of talking about all of them now,
I will introduce them throughout the course
as they become relevant.
That being said, I do encourage you to check
out the list of data types within the documentation,
just so you know which ones are available.
There are some pretty cool ones for specific
use cases that I won’t have time to cover
in this course.
I’ve attached the link to this lecture.
Instead of spending time on covering these
basic data types extensively, let’s move
on to some data types that are a bit more
complex.
First, we have the “object” data type.
This data type essentially just covers any
JSON object.
Each document that we index into Elasticsearch
is a JSON object.
This document may then contain a field with
an object as its value.
This object may then contain an inner object
itself, forming an object hierarchy.
In other words, you can nest objects.
The way this is mapped, is that a “properties”
key is added for objects instead of specifying
the “type” key as with other data types.
The type is therefore not just set to “object”
as you might have expected.
“properties” is actually a mapping parameter,
but we will get to that soon.
We then define the keys that the object contains
within this “properties” key.
The same is the case if this inner object
contains an inner object itself.
Notice how we also did this for the fields
at the root level of the mapping.
Don’t worry if you find this syntax confusing
at first; it does take a bit of time to get used to.
Even though we just define objects as regular
JSON objects when we index documents, that’s
actually not how the objects are stored internally.
As you know, Elasticsearch is built on top
of Apache Lucene, which does not support objects.
That’s why Elasticsearch transforms inner
objects to a format that is compatible with
Lucene, as part of indexing operations.
The reason for that is to ensure that we can
index any document that is valid according
to the JSON specification.
This makes Elasticsearch easier to use, because
we don’t need to structure documents in
any special way to ensure that they can be
indexed into Apache Lucene.
The way the objects are stored internally,
is that they are flattened.
Each level in the hierarchy is denoted with
a dot, such that there are no longer any objects,
but the hierarchy is maintained.
This way, object fields can now be stored
within Apache Lucene, and we can still query
fields as if they were objects by using a
dot notation syntax.
That’s great, but what happens if we try
to index an array of objects?
How are the objects flattened then?
Wouldn’t the result be duplicate field names?
The answer to the last question is yes.
What happens is that the values are grouped
by field name and indexed as an array.
If you run a search query against one of the
fields, it will search through all of the
values within the array.
That’s pretty nice in some situations, but
it can cause trouble in others.
Let’s look at an example.
Suppose that we want to search for products
that have a review left by a person named
John Doe, with a rating of at least 4.
The query is pretty simple, but since we haven’t
gotten to search queries yet, the one you
will see is just a pseudo query.
What will happen, is that the product will
match, even though the review left by John
Doe actually has a rating of 3.5.
The reason is that the field values were all
mixed together when the document was indexed,
so the relationship between the object keys
was lost.
When this happens, Elasticsearch doesn’t
know that there is a relationship between
“John Doe” and 3.5.
What we intended to do, was to match products
containing a review written by John Doe and
with a rating of at least 4.
What actually happened was that we matched
products containing a review written by John
Doe or with a rating of at least 4.
This essentially means that the boolean AND
was effectively turned into a boolean OR due
to how the values are stored internally.
That’s probably not what we want, and it’s
definitely not the behavior that you would
To solve this, there is a data type called
“nested,” which is a specialized version
of the “object” data type.
The purpose of it is to maintain the relationship
between object values when an array of objects
is indexed.
Using this data type enables us to query objects
independently, meaning that the object values
are not mixed together as you saw a moment
ago.
To utilize this data type, we must use a specific
query, which you will see later in the course.
On your screen you can see an example of using
this data type.
The data type is simply set to “nested”
in the same way as for other data types.
Using the pseudo query from before, it would
only match products containing a review written
by John Doe and with a rating greater than
or equal to 4.
That’s because the objects are stored independently
and the query then behaves how we probably
have expected it to in the first place.
Unlike before, the product is therefore not
matched by the query.
I mentioned that Apache Lucene has no concept
of objects, so how are these objects stored?
They are actually stored as hidden documents.
And yes, by documents, I mean documents just
like the ones we indexed.
The difference is that these documents won’t
show up in search results unless we query
them directly.
Suppose that we index a product containing
ten reviews, each being a nested object.
This would cause 11 documents to be indexed
into Lucene; one for the product, and one
for each review.
The last data type I want to talk about is
the one named “keyword.”
This data type should be used for fields on
which you want to search for exact values.
Since only exact searching is supported, this
data type is used for filtering, sorting,
and aggregating documents.
An example would be to have a “status”
field for news articles and search for all
articles that have a value of “published”
for the field.
If you want to perform so-called full-text
searches, you need to use the “text” data
type instead.
Full-text searches are basically searches
that do not require exact matches.
For instance, we could search for news articles
containing one or more specific words within
their contents.
We will dive deeper into the difference between
the “text” and “keyword” data types
in the next lecture.
The takeaway for now is that the “keyword”
data type is used for sorting, filtering,
and aggregations.
That’s a quick overview of the most important
data types in Elasticsearch.
Like I said, I encourage you to check out
the documentation to see which ones are available.