In the previous lecture, I briefly mentioned
the use case for the “keyword” data type,
being filtering, sorting, and aggregations.
But why is its use limited to this?
Why can’t we use it for full-text searches
as with the “text” data type?
To answer those questions, we need to dive
into how “keyword” fields are analyzed and stored.
Previously you saw how the “standard”
analyzer is used for “text” fields.
For “keyword” fields, however, an analyzer
named “keyword” is used instead.
This analyzer is actually a so-called no-op
analyzer, meaning that it doesn’t do anything.
Well, besides returning the unmodified input
string as a single token.
The string is not modified in any way, because
it is intended for exact matching.
We can verify this by using the Analyze API
that I showed you a bit earlier.
I have prepared the query for doing so, so
let’s just go ahead and run it.
As you can see, the string is left entirely
untouched and is just returned as a single token.
If symbols were to be stripped out, for instance,
we wouldn’t be able to perform exact searches.
Why?
Because the values within the inverted index
would then differ from the string that was
provided within the indexed document.
Searching for the original value would therefore
yield no results.
Speaking of the inverted index, let’s have
a look at what it would look like a couple
of documents.
As you can see, the entire field values are
stored as a single term.
This is unlike the “text” fields where
the “standard” analyzer is used.
Apart from tokenization, we can also see how
the “keyword” analyzer does not remove
any symbols from the string, and neither does
it lowercase letters.
This example is good for understanding that
text is left completely untouched when using
the “keyword” data type.
However, it doesn’t demonstrate a realistic
use case for a “keyword” field, since
no one is realistically going to search for
exactly those sentences.
A much more realistic use case would be to
map something like e-mail addresses or article
statuses as a “keyword” field.
Let’s go with a couple of documents representing
users, each containing an e-mail address.
And here is what the inverted index for the
“email” field would look like.
This is a much better use case, because you
will almost always want to do exact matches
on these kinds of values.
Notice how one of the e-mail addresses contains
uppercase letters.
Often that’s what you want with “keyword”
fields, but in some scenarios it might make
sense to lowercase letters.
That would make sense in this example, because
e-mail addresses are not case sensitive.
Apart from building custom analyzers, it’s
also possible to configure existing ones.
This means that we can configure the “keyword”
analyzer to use the “lowercase” token
filter, causing the inverted index to look
like this instead.
I will show you how to configure analyzers
later in this section, so I just wanted to
mention the possibility now.
Alright, let’s quickly summarize what we
covered in this lecture.
Fields that use the “keyword” data type
are analyzed using the “keyword” analyzer.
All this analyzer does, is to output the input
string as a single token, with everything
left untouched.
This single token is then placed within the
inverted index for the field.
That’s why the “keyword” data type is
used for exact matching and things like sorting
and aggregations.
Basically structured data, which could be
e-mail addresses, order statuses, product tags, etc.