Now that you know about the most important
data types, I want to tell you about something
called type coercion.
As you know, Elasticsearch checks the data
types for each field value when we index adocument.
A part of this process is to validate the
data types and reject field values that are
obviously invalid.
An example of that would be trying to index
an object for a text field.
Sometimes we can get away with providing the
wrong data type, though.
Let’s head over to Kibana so I can show
you an example instead of just talking about it.
Here I have three queries prepared, which
index three documents into a new throwaway index.
We haven’t created this index, so it will
be created automatically when indexing the
first document as I told you earlier in the
course.
Let’s run the first query.
The index has now been created and the document
has been indexed into it, so no surprises
so far.
A mapping for the “price” field has actually
been created due to dynamic mapping, which
you will learn more about soon.
What Elasticsearch did, was to inspect the
value that we supplied in order to figure
out its data type.
In this case we supplied a floating point
number, so the “float” data type was used
within the mapping.
As for the next query, you have probably noticed
how the floating point number has been wrapped
within double quotes, effectively turning
it into a string value.
What do you think will happen when we run
the query?
Well, let’s try.
The document was indexed correctly even though
we supplied a string value instead of a floating
point number.
This is where type coercion comes into the
picture.
Elasticsearch first resolves the data type
that was supplied for a given field.
In the case where there is a mapping for the
field, the two data types are compared.
Since we supplied a string for a numeric data
type, Elasticsearch inspects the string value.
If it contains a numeric value — and only
a numeric value — Elasticsearch will convert
the string to the correct data type, being
“float” in this example.
The result is that a string of 7.4 is converted
into the floating point number 7.4 instead,
and the document is indexed as if we had supplied
a number in the first place.
So what happens if we supply a string containing
something that cannot be converted to a float?
Well, I’m sure you can imagine, but let’s
try.
As you can see, the query failed because the
data type was incorrect, and Elasticsearch
was unable to coerce the value into the appropriate
data type.
Let’s retrieve the second document that
we indexed, because I want to show you something.
Notice how the value within the source document
is a string and not a float.
Didn’t I just tell you that Elasticsearch
coerces the value into a float instead of
a string?
I did, but there’s actually a good explanation.
The reason is that the “_source” key contains
the original values that we indexed.
These are not the values that Elasticsearch
uses internally when searching for data.
Can you guess where I’m going with this?
Elasticsearch searches the data structure
used by Apache Lucene to store the field values.
In the case of text fields, that would be
an inverted index.
In this example, the value has been converted
into a float, even though we see a string
here.
Within Apache Lucene, the value is stored
as a numeric value and not a string.
This means that if you make use of the value
within the “_source” key, you need to
be aware that the value may be either a float
or a string, depending on the value that was
supplied at index time.
If this is a problem for you, you either need
to supply the correct data type in the first
place, or disable coercion, which I will show
you how to do a bit later.
In this lecture, you saw how coercion works
in the case of converting strings to floats.
Another example of coercion could be to supply
a floating point for an integer field, in
which case the float will be truncated to
an integer value.
One important thing to mention is that coercion
is not used when figuring out which data type
to use for a field with dynamic mapping.
This means that if you supply a string value,
the data type will be set to “text” even
if the string only contains a number.
In general you should always try to use the
correct data types.
It’s especially important when you index
a new field, to ensure that the correct data
type is used in the mapping — provided that
you make use of dynamic mapping.
Anyway, the point is that Elasticsearch does
not use coercion when creating field mappings
for us; it’s only used as a convenience
that forgives us if we use the wrong data
types.
Whether or not you should disable coercion
is a matter of preference.
I personally prefer to disable it, just to
ensure that Elasticsearch always receives
the data type that it’s supposed to; otherwise
I prefer an error to be thrown so that it
can be fixed.
Coercion is enabled by default to make Elasticsearch
as easy and forgiving as possible, but you
will see how to disable it a bit later.
The last thing I will do in this lecture,
is to get rid of the index that we just created,
since we won’t be using it again.