A moment ago we covered the most important
data types.
Among those were basic data types such as
text, integer, boolean, date, etc.
But what if we want to store multiple values
for a field?
Perhaps you noticed that I didn’t mention
any “array” data type.
There’s a good reason for that; it doesn’t
exist.
That’s because any field in Elasticsearch
may contain zero or more values by default.
That’s right - you can index an array of values without defining this within the field’s mapping.
We actually did that in the previous section
where we indexed a “tags” field for products.
All we did was to supply an array as the field
value, and everything worked out of the box.
This means that both of these two queries
are valid, and you can run them in any order.
The “tags” field will be mapped as a “text”
field, so we don’t define that the value
may contain multiple values; that’s just
how Elasticsearch works by default.
The mapping would just look as follows.
As you can see, there is no sign of an “array”
data type or the likes anywhere.
So how is this stored internally, you might
wonder?
In the case of text fields, the strings are
simply concatenated before being analyzed,
and the resulting tokens are stored within
an inverted index as normal.
We can verify that this is the case by using
the Analyze API.
Here I have a simple query that specifies
an array of two strings instead of just a
single string.
To the right, we can see that the results
contain tokens from both strings.
Notice the character offsets for the last
two tokens, originating from the second string.
The offsets don’t start over from zero,
but rather continue from the last offset of
the first string.
I hope that makes sense.
This means that the strings are indeed treated
as a single string and not as multiple values.
I should mention that the strings are concatenated
with a space in-between, because otherwise
the words “simply” and “merged” would
end up within the same token.
In the case of non-text fields, the values
are not analyzed, and multiple values are
just stored within the appropriate data structure
within Apache Lucene.
Anyway, enough about how the values are stored.
There is one constraint when using arrays
that you should be aware of; all of the values
within the array must be of the same data
type.
This means that you cannot mix strings and
integers together in the same array, for instance.
Well, I said that data types cannot be mixed,
but that is not 100% true.
You can mix data types together as long as
the provided types can be coerced into the
data type used within the mapping.
That’s of course assuming that coercion
is enabled.
Consider the following arrays, for example.
While it’s certainly not ideal, these arrays
will work, because the values that have a
wrong data type, can all be coerced into the
right one.
That’s usually the case for simple data
types, but not for other ones such as objects.
In this example, Elasticsearch has no way
of coercing a boolean into an object, and
so it will return an error.
An important thing to note is that coercion
of array values is only supported when a mapping
has already been created, either explicitly
or through dynamic mapping.
If you index a field for the first time and
no mapping already exists, it will be created
automatically with dynamic mapping.
However, in this case you are not allowed
to supply mixed data types; that’s only
allowed when indexing documents after the
mapping has been created.
I don’t recommend relying on coercion, but
if you do, make sure that you provide the
correct data type for all array values until
the field mapping has been created.
It’s also possible to index nested arrays, such as the example that you see on your screen now.
Supplying such an array will cause Elasticsearch
to flatten it, i.e. to move any nested array
values up to the top level.
As a last thing, I just want to remind you
that if you index an array of objects, you
need to use the “nested” type if you want
to query the objects independently.
This is just a reminder of what we discussed
in a previous lecture.
If you don’t need to query the objects independently,
you can just use the “object” data type.
And that’s all there is to arrays, so let’s
continue.