Now that you know how Elasticsearch handles
modifying data in a replicated setup, let’s
see how it searches for data.
Let’s begin with what you will typically
see as a developer running search queries
towards an Elasticsearch cluster.
You have some kind of client, which will often
be a server.
That client communicates with the Elasticsearch
cluster by sending search queries over HTTP.
The cluster then does its magic based on the index
and query that you have specified in the HTTP request.
When the results are ready, the cluster responds
with the results, and the client can use the
results for whatever purpose.
For a lot of people, that’s all they really
need to know.
If you just need to run some queries against
an Elasticsearch cluster, then this may be
sufficient for you, because in that case you
are mostly concerned with writing the queries
and not how Elasticsearch gathers the results
internally.
That being said, I have always been a fan
of digging a bit deeper and understanding
the tools that you use, because this will
often be helpful in the long run.
Let’s therefore take a peek inside the cluster
and see what happens when it receives a search query.
Suppose we have a cluster consisting of three
nodes containing one index distributed across
three shards - shard A, B and C. Each shard has
two replicas, so each replication group consists
of a primary shard and two replicas.
Then suppose that a client sends a search
query to the cluster which ends up on the
node containing Shard B.
This node is now the so-called "coordinating
node," meaning that this node is responsible
for sending queries to other nodes, assembling
the results and responding to the client.
So basically coordinating the query, hence
the name “coordinating node.”
By default, every node may act as the coordinating
node and may receive HTTP requests as I mentioned
a bit earlier.
Since the coordinating node itself contains
a shard which should be searched, the node
will perform the query itself.
This may not be the case in other scenarios,
but since we only have one index, this will
always be the case.
The coordinating node then broadcasts the
request to every other shard in the index,
being either a primary shard or a replica
shard.
In this example I have just shown that the
primary shards receive the requests, i.e.
Shard A and C, but this could just as well
have been replicas for the shards.
Also note that how the coordinating node determines
which shards - and thereby nodes - the request
should be sent to, is outside the scope of
this lecture, so that’s not something that
we will look at for now.
Right now, the important thing is to understand
the flow of search queries, more than to understand
every detail.
When the other shards respond with each of
their results, the coordinating node merges
them together and sorts them, and lastly returns
the results to the client.
Just to quickly repeat the steps to make
sure that it is clear.
A search query hits a given node within the
cluster.
This node becomes the coordinating node for
the query.
It broadcasts the request to all shards in
the index that the query refers to.
This can be both primary shards and replica
shards.
These shards then respond with the results,
and the coordinating node will merge all of
the results together into a single result,
which is then returned to the client.
As a last thing, I just want to mention that
the approach is different if you retrieve
a single document by its ID.
When doing this, the request is routed to
the appropriate shard instead of being broadcasted
to all of the index’ shards.
In the next lecture, I will briefly explain
how routing works at a high level.