In this section, we are going to look at so-called
joining queries.
We have covered a lot about searching for
documents already, but now we are going to
look at querying relationships between documents.
In this introductory lecture, I am just going
to briefly show you a couple of examples of
how data can be stored in a relational database
such as MySQL og Postgres.
Suppose that we want to store employees in
a database, and that each employee is associated
with an address.
In relational databases, it’s best practice
to normalize data, meaning that we can store
this data in two different tables and link
the two with a foreign key.
Relational databases are all about creating
and querying relationships between different
pieces of data, hence the name relational
databases.
Or perhaps we want to store the departments
of companies and which cities they are located
within, in which case the database schema
could look something like this.
In this case, each department has a foreign
key to the city that it is located in, meaning
that we are dealing with a one-to-many relationship.
Okay, so why am I talking about relational
databases all of a sudden?
Because most developers are familiar with
relational databases, and I want to tell you
that this is not how you go about storing
data in Elasticsearch.
In Elasticsearch, you generally denormalize
your data whenever possible, because that
leads to the best performance, so kind of the opposite of what you would do in a relational database.
To give you a comparison, how you store data
in Elasticsearch is close to how you would
store data in a NoSQL database such as MongoDB
where you either don’t join data at all,
or do it at the application level.
But isn’t storing data in a denormalized
way inefficient, you might wonder?
Won’t we be wasting disk space by storing
the city name for each department instead
of having a foreign key point to it and thereby
only store it one time?
Yes, that’s true, but remember that it’s
generally not recommended to use Elasticsearch
as a primary data store.
By not doing this, we have the freedom to
store data however we want within Elasticsearch,
i.e. in ways that are optimized for quickly
searching for data.
So in this case, it might be perfectly fine
to sacrifice disk space to increase the performance
and throughput of the Elasticsearch cluster.
Elasticsearch doesn’t support joins like
relational databases do, but it does support
some simple ways of joining documents.
It has to be said, though, that these queries
are pretty inefficient, so that might be worth
keeping in mind when dealing with lots of
documents.
So how can we map and query document relationships
in Elasticsearch?
Let’s take a look at which tools we have
at our disposal in the following lectures.