Now that you know how to use joining queries
and how to map document relationships, let’s
talk a bit about the performance of these
queries.
Note that in this lecture, I am talking specifically
about the performance of the "join" field,
i.e. parent/child joins, and not the "nested"
query.
Well, let me just begin by summarizing the
takeaway from this lecture; join queries are
expensive in terms of performance and should
be avoided whenever possible.
There are a few cases where using join fields
makes sense, but in general they should be
used with caution.
Of course this is a slight simplification,
as it also depends how much data you are dealing with.
If you don’t care for the details of this,
then you are welcome to skip the remainder
of this lecture.
Otherwise, let’s dive into a bit more detail.
Like I said, using "join" fields is slow.
For example, the performance of the "has_child"
query degrades the more child documents that
point to unique parent documents.
Essentially the query just gets slower the
more documents you add to an index that uses
a "join" field.
You won’t notice this in the beginning,
but as the number of documents increases,
you will start to see increasing query times,
which will eventually become quite significant.
The same applies for the "has_parent"
query, where the number of parent documents
affects performance negatively.
Apart from that, if you make use of multi-level
relations, then each level of relation adds
an overhead to your queries, so you should
almost always avoid this.
That being said, there is a scenario where
it makes sense to use a "join" field and
where the performance will still be good.
That’s if you have a one-to-many relationship
between two document types and there are significantly
more of one type than the other.
Having recipes as the parent documents and
ingredients as child documents, is a good
candidate for using a "join" field, because
there are going to be significantly more ingredients
than recipes.
You could also map the ingredients as nested
objects if you wanted to, but the point is
that it would also be fine to use a "join"
field in this case.
Alright, so now that you know a bit more about
the implications of using "join" fields,
there are two more questions left to be answered.
The first one is: if using "join" fields
is usually discouraged, then why on Earth
did I just spend so much time talking about
it?
Well, because there are still times where
it’s perfectly fine to make use of parent/child
relations, such as in the example that I told
you about a moment ago.
And also if you have limited number of documents
and don’t anticipate that it’s going to change much.
Secondly, it’s still a part of Elasticsearch,
and it’s not my job to decide how you are
going to map your documents.
That’s also impossible, as every use case
is different.
It is, however, my responsibility to give
you the tools that you need to make a qualified
decision and my recommendations, but in the
end the choice is yours.
The other question is: if "join" fields
are usually not a good idea to use, then how
do we map document relationships properly?
Well, for one, we have the "nested" data
type, but that might not always suit your needs.
So generally speaking, you shouldn’t map
document relationships.
Elasticsearch is very efficient for searching
through tons of data, but Elasticsearch is
a very different technology than a relational
database, for instance.
This means that you should store data as a
structure that is optimized for efficient searching.
I mentioned this in one of the first lectures
of the course, but now seems like an appropriate
time to recap on that.
Suppose that you want to map employees as
documents.
Instead of having the employee’s address
as a stand-alone document, you can either
map it as a nested object, or you can just
add the fields like any other fields.
The point is that you denormalize the data
instead of trying to map document relationships,
because that’s not how things are supposed
to be done in Elasticsearch, at least generally speaking.
So unless you have a good reason for using
"join" fields, try to just denormalize
your data and use "join" fields whenever
that doesn’t work for you, and you can accept
the consequences and limitations of using
"join" fields.