The first step to defining document relationships,
is to define them in the mapping.
Because we need to change the mapping,
I have deleted the department index in advance,
just to make things easier for ourselves.
The way we can join documents in Elasticsearch
is by using a special kind of field called a join field.
This field defines the relations between the types
of documents that are part of the document hierarchy.
Let's get started adding the mapping for the field
and I'll share a few more details
about the field afterwards.
We can name the field anything we want,
exactly as any other field, so I'll just name it join_field.
So I'll write join_field here
and give it a value of an object.
The data type for this field is join,
which is a special data type that's dedicated
for defining document relationships.
So I'll define that through the type object
and set it to join.
The possible relations between the various kinds
of documents must then be defined within a relations object,
so let's go ahead and add that object.
So relations, and I'll set it to an empty object for now.
This object should contain key-value pairs
defining the relationships between documents.
Let's continue with the example from the previous lecture
and add a relationship between a department and an employee.
We can do that by adding a key
with a value of department and a value of employee,
so let's do that.
So department, and employee as the value.
These are just arbitrary strings of our choice
and the key does not need to match the name of the index
as it does in this example.
That's it!
Let's go ahead and run the query.
Okay, so what does this actually mean?
We have just defined two relation types,
being department and employee,
where department is the parent of employee.
This means that we have effectively
defined a parent-child relationship
which we can make use of when adding documents.
The relation that we defined
is between a parent and a child,
but we could also have defined
multiple children if we wanted to.
All we had to do for that, would be
to change the string value with an array of strings instead.
That way, each of the strings within the array
represents a child document type belonging to the parent.
Anyways, the relation that we did create
enables us to query documents based on the relationship,
which you will see in a couple of lectures.
But first, let's add some documents to the index
so that we have some data to work with.